<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Zealous beleevers are the best subjects to Cæser or An exhortation to all good Christians to pray for their princes : there being nothing wherein they can better shew their allegiance. Published invindication [sic] of the saints against the false imputations of such as count it rebellion to be religious. / by I.F.</title>
            <author>Ferret, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1103_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208364</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867321</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867321</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119628</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85238)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 163:E1103[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Zealous beleevers are the best subjects to Cæser or An exhortation to all good Christians to pray for their princes : there being nothing wherein they can better shew their allegiance. Published invindication [sic] of the saints against the false imputations of such as count it rebellion to be religious. / by I.F.</title>
                  <author>Ferret, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>134, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted in the yeare, 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I. F. = John Ferret.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119628:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Zealous Beleevers</hi> are <hi>The best Subjects</hi> to CAESAR Or <hi>An exhortation to all good Chriſtians to pray for their princes: there being nothing wherein they can better shew their allegiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed <hi>Invindication of the Saints againſt the falſe imputations of ſuch as count it rebellion to be religious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>by <hi>I. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted in the yeare,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Scriptural_citations">
            <pb facs="tcp:119628:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 120: 2. 5. 6. 7.</bibl>
               <p>DEliver my ſoul, ô Lord from lying, lips, and from a deceiptfull tongue. VVo is me that I ſojourn in Meſech: that I dwell in the tents of Redar. My ſoul hath long dwelt with him that hateth peace. I am for peace: but when I ſpeake they are for warre.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Revel. 3: 8. 9. 10. 11.</bibl>
               <p>I Know they works; behold I have ſet before thee an open doore, and no man can shut it: for thou hast a little ſtrength, and hast kept my word, and hast not denyed my name. Behold I will make them of the Synagogue of Satan, which ſay they are Iews, and are not, but doe lye: behold I will make them to come, and worship before thy feet, and to know that I have loved thee. Becaus thou hast kept the word of my patience, I alſo will keep thee from the houre of tentation, which shall come upon all the world, to try them that dwell upon the Earth. Behold I come quickly: hold that fast which thou hast; that no man take thy crowne.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119628:2"/>
            <head>To the right worshipful John Browne Eſquire Lord of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Frampton in the county of Dorſet, and one of his Majeſty's Iuſtices of peace for the ſame coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, grace and peace from him that is, that was, and that is to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I could have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed this ſmall treatiſe without any particuler dedication, but that the remembrance of the manyfold favours which I have from my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119628:3"/> childhood untill now receaved from your worp, and your worthy family, obligeth me to make ſome publike acknowledgment thereof, leaſt I ſhould be unthankfull: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireing therein to imitate the example of the bleſſed <note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1: 16. 17. 18.</note> Apoſtle towards Oneſiphorus; whom, I am commanded to <note n="b" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11: 1.</note> 
               <hi>follow as he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Chriſt.</hi> Luke dedicated his Euangelicall hiſtorie to his noble Theophilus, Paul an epiſtle to his beloved fellow-labourer Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon, and the Diſciple whom Jeſus loved a letter to Gajus his hoſt; and why not I this homely piece (which is of publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernement) to you my noble land-lord, to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> I owe (by the law of our la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>) both ſuite and ſervice? W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch ſeing I am (by the calling wherein God hath ſet me) reſtrained from civile performance of, I can not but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119628:3"/> think my ſelf bound to doe you ſervice in that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I have. Sir, I have bin the more earneſtly provoked hereunto, by ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation which I have lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved, of your being a member of that ho<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> houſe of Commons now aſſembled in Parliament, and intruſted with the care of our County, in helping to reform and ſettle the preſent enormities and diſtractions. I know that many invective ſpeeches (whereof that honourable Court is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant) have bin caſt out ſince theſe troubles began; againſt the way <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 24: 14.</note> 
               <hi>wherein I worship the God of my fathers, believing all things which are written in the law and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> which is by manie accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hereſy and doctrine of <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lue.</hi> 23: 2.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; and men are prone by nature to follow the voice of the <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 23: 2.</note> multitude, and very eaſily to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119628:4"/> be drawen to condemne that which <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude vers</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>they know not.</hi> To the end therfore that your worſhip and that ho: <hi rend="sup">ble</hi> court with you may not (through miſſe-information) <hi>call</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5: 20.</note> 
               <hi>light darknes,</hi> and condemne the innocent without cauſe; I have bin conſtrained out of <note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5: 14.</note> love to God, and for the honour of the truth, to caſt my mite into the Lord's treaſurie; and to give you a taſt of the fidelity and loyaltie of thoſe that doe truly profeſſe ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from Babylon (ſpiritually ſo called) to the higher powers. Who, if they ſhall nevertheleſſe be ſtill condemned as evill-doers; yet, I hope, by their patient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and <note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3: 16.</note> good converſation, ſhall in the end make their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes aſhamed, who falſely accuſe them. The religious carriage w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I have in my youth alwayes noted in your wor:p, and your whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119628:4"/> &amp; the redreſſing of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profanation of the Lord's day and other profaneneſſe in the place where you have authority, at your firſt coming to the enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the eſtate of your decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed father (like an other <note n="k" place="margin">Nehem. 13: 15. 16. 17. &amp;c.</note> Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah) wherin I hope you perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, maketh me to be confidently perſwaded of many good things which the Lord hath wrought in you, and that you wilbe an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the hand of the Lord, to countenance and incourage ſuch as walke in his feare. Worthy Sir, if this my indeavor may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God and you, and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable to anie, I have my reward. In the meane time though I am abſent in the body, yet I ſhall not forget to commend you and your whole family, and the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of that honourable Court wherof you are a member (if I be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119628:5"/> not miſinformed) togither with the preſent calamities of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive country, unto Almightie God in my daylie prayers; and be ready to doe you and them any ſervice in the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. F.</signed>
               <dateline>Amsterdam in Holland <date>this 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the 5 moneth called May 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119628:5"/>
            <head>To the well-adviſed Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ever man might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelf of ſpeaking in the cauſe of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the princes and people of the earth, by ſaying</hi> I am not eloquent, but ſlow of ſpeech, &amp; of a ſlow tongue. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4: 10. <hi>or</hi> Ah Lord, God! behold I can not ſpeake; for I am a child, <hi>Ierem. 1: 6. then may I: who am conſtrayned (by the knowledge of myne owne weakneſſe) to confeſſe my ſelf of all men most unworthy to open my mouth in the gates. For the which cauſe I have (though often moved by the preſent diſtractions, to ſpeake in way of defence of the goſpell of Chriſt, which now undergoeth as great reproach and as unadviſed cenſures as ever) reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the bewraying of myne owne illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature and weakneſſe to the world; ſtill hoping that God would ſtirre up
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119628:6"/> ſome more able inſtrument to have mynded thoſe things whereon I have had ſome thoughts, and to have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished that which might have bin ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitient to remove the ſtumbling block. But having hitherto failed of my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, and the fire ſtill burning within me (Pſal. 39: 3.) I have now at length adventured to eaſe my mynd in this homely treatiſe. Wherein (Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous reader) thou hast the ſubstance of ſome doctrines which were long ſince delivered (on a day of publike prayer commanded by the ſtates of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands for the good ſucceſſe of thoſe Countries againſt their enemyes) to a Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of beleevers who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly (but corruptly) called Brownists, ſome of whome have bin many yeares a goe banished out of their owne native Country for the profeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the goſpell, and not to this day called home again, though they may ſay with the prophet Daniel that</hi> before God innocency
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119628:6"/> was found in them, and before the King they had done no hurt, <hi>Dan. 6: 22. wherfore the Lord hath preſerved them unto this day, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for them an hiding place from the ſtormie wynds and tempests of his wrath, which are fallen upon our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Region. And who can tell but this may be a ſcourge upon them for their banishing and cruell perſecuting of the Saints, whoſe cauſe the Lord doth to this day justifie by his gratious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations toward them, and whoſe</hi> righteouſnes he ſhall bring forth<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37: 6. 9. 39. 40.</note> as the light, and their judgment as the noone day; for evill doers ſhalbe cut off: but thoſe that wait upon the Lord, they ſhall inherite the Earth. For the ſalvation of the righteous is of the Lord: he is their ſtrength in time of trouble, and the Lord ſhall helpe them and deliver them: he ſhall deliver them from the wicked, and ſave
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119628:7"/> them, becaus they truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In this treatiſe thou mayest plainly perceave, if thou be not prejudiced by partiallity or worldly mindedneſſe, how unjustly the people of that profeſsion (eſpetially thoſe that ſojourne at Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam) are charged of being distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Commonweale, and enemyes to Kingly powers on earth, whiles they approve ſuch doctrine to be taught amongſt them, as hath bin alwayes their profeſsion from their firſt ſeparation from the Church of England, as may be ſeen by their Apologie or defence pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished againſt the groundleſſe imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Oxford-doctors in the yeare 1604. and dedicated to K. Iames of famous memory. By which Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie thou maist perceive, for whom it is that I make this defence, not for all that are called Brownists (for I must confeſſe with the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſvv. to the K. decla. concering his victory. Oct.</hi> 3. 1642.</note> 
               <hi>honourable court of Parliament of England, that there are many now a dayes that goe under
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119628:7"/> the name of Brownists that come farre short of the principles which thoſe which heretofore have only had that name cast upon them doe hold, ſuch as are Semi-ſeperatiſts as they are termed, who can hold one foot in the Church of God and the other in the Synagogue of Satan, partake of the Lords table and the table of divels, and many for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſors, whom I leave to ſtand or fall to their owne maſter, knowing that</hi> God is alſo able to make them ſtand, <hi>Rom. 14: 4.) but only for a ſmall company of poore deſpiſed Chriſtians, who are constrayned to dwell in a ſtrange Country</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1: 9.</note> for the word of God and for the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>But bleſſed be the great God of heaven and earth</hi> the father of mercies the God of all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion who alwaies cauſeth them to <note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2: 14.</note> tryumph in Chriſt, <hi>and hath</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1: 4.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted them in all their tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, and made them able to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119628:8"/> comfort others that have bin i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> trouble by the comfort where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they themſelves are comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the ſubſtance of the treatiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hope thou shalt find it agreable te</hi> the <note n="a" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4: 11.</note> word of God; <hi>for I deſire to utte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothing in publike, but what the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture hath first ſpoken, or endited to me by which</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2: 29.</note> the Spirit ſpeaketh unto the churches. <hi>But beautifull o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loftie ſtile (to pleaſe humane phanta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſies) thou mayst not expect from on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is no ſcholler in humane ſciences and ſtudyeth for no greater learning than to ſpeak the truth in plain English nor ſuch ſobriety and gravity as dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> befit ſo weighty a ſubje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, from one th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is ſo tender in age, and hath bin bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> foure yeares in the ſchoole of Christ and is full of like</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 14: 15.</note> 
               <hi>paſsions and huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne infirmities as other men are. Wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore if any thing be let fall through m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unadviſedneſſe herein, not beſeemin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119628:8"/> the goſpell of Chriſt, and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the ſame, I know thoſe that feare God will not rejoyce in it, and the wiſe will lovingly reprove me for it; and I (by God's grace) shalbe ready to acknowledge it, and an other time to amend it if I can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have bin moved to the publishing hereof by the divers ſpeeches, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations which have bin given out (on all handes) in theſe troubleſome times, wherein thoſe that feare God and ſeperate from ſin as much as in them is, have bin inveighed againſt, as a companie of ſciſmaticall, and troubleſome ſpirits to the State. Yea writings have bin published in the name of the King's moſt excellent maieſty (whom we ought all under God to reverence as the father of our Country and God's vicegerent in his dominions) wherein have bin great imputations of evill against ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Brownists, as if they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119628:9"/> and Anabaptiſts with the aſsiſtance of</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>K. Declar. against the Parl. aſſeſsing dat. Dec. 8. 1642. Pag.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>vitious and deboished perſons of deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate fortunes take upon them to breake up &amp; rifle houſes, as publike &amp; avowed miniſters of a new invented authority &amp;c. and afterwards it is ſaid, whilſt Sciſmaticall, illiterate, and ſcandalous preachers fill their pulpits &amp; churches with blaſphemy, irreverence, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and incite their auditors to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but murder and rebellion, &amp;c. And again pag. 7. Theſe are the men who joyning with the Anabaptiſts and Brownists of London firſt changed the governement and diſcipline of that City, would undoe the Kingdome, &amp;c. And ſome thing I have read in ſome former writings, ſtriking at the godly people at Amſterdam alſo, as if they were the originall of theſe ſtirs and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults (when as it is nothing els but for the ſins of the land that God's hand is ſtretched out againſt them) Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is imputed as a blame to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119628:9"/> Parliament and city of London, that they maintaine &amp; countenance Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts &amp;c. See declar: of vict: Oct. 3. 1642. and his Majesties anſwere to the Cities petition for peace, read in a Common hall, &amp;c. Now the law hath required me, not to revile or</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod. 22<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 28. Acts.</hi> 23: 5.</note> curſe the ruler of my people, <hi>neither can I eaſily be brought to think that theſe expreſsions proceeded originally out of his princely heart; which if yet they did, farre be it from me to cenſure him for them in my</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 20.</note> 
               <hi>thoughts. I have alſo heard and underſtood, and the current of writings maketh me ſomewhat to credit it, that it is a common practiſe of their parſons and vicars in their pulpits (that they may curry favour with the bad counſillers about the King) to inveigh againſt Browniſts and Seperatiſts, as the only ſeditious and rebellious perſons of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But by the following treatiſe thou majeſt plainly perceave (gentle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119628:10"/> reader) that whoſoever are guilty of thoſe faults; yet that poore Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for whom I plead, who have their habitation in a farre Country are free and innocent of the ſame, and are ſuch as doe neither plot or countenance the plotting of any evill, or ſowe any ſeed of rebellion againſt the higher powers, but doe owe and acknowledge them all due reverence, as alſo the law requireth, and their carriage doth witnes for them in the place where they dwell, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all dutyes of honour and office, without complaint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have therefore cumbered the preſſe herewith, fearing leaſt any should either be diſcouraged by theſe rumor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſlaunders (which are and have bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hitherto caſt upon us) from imbracing the truth, and walking in the right way or should through miſſe-reports con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the righteous with the guilty and alſo to ſtop the mouthes of gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, who if (notwithſtanding the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119628:10"/> shall ſee this defence) they doe ſtill perſist in their opprobrious calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, shalbe left without excuſe before the face of God</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whoſe judgment is according to truth againſt thoſe that commit ſuch things. <hi>I have ſought herein, nothing, but the glory of God, and the vindication of the truth from unjust contempt; which if it shall notwithſtanding ſuffer, I shall deſire of God that I may be accounted worthy to ſuffer with it. And for a concluſion, it is myne heartie deſire, that all people whatſoever which doe make any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of the truth may approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuch in their converſations, as</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 24: 21.</note> feare God and honour the King and meddle not with them that are given to change: <hi>but</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12: 14</note> follow peace with all men and holynes, without which no man can ſee the Lord, <hi>medling w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> their own callings, and be not buſy bodies in other mens matters, that thoſe which</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3: 16.</note> ſpeak evill of them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119628:11"/> may be aſhamed who falſly accuſe their good converſation in Chriſt. <hi>But if any of them doe under colour of religion or Conſcience, reſiſt the lawfull commands of their prince or gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and doe ſuffer for it, let them thanke themſelves, and confeſſe the juſtice of God upon them, for</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13: 4.</note> they are his miniſters, appointed to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute vengeance on them that doe evill, and they beare not the ſword in vaine.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 Tim. 2: 7.</bibl>
                  <p>Conſider what I ſay: and the Lord giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thee underſtanding in all things.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 Theſſ. 5: 21.</bibl>
                  <p>Prove all things: hold fast that which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119628:11"/>
            <head>An exhortation to pray for Princes.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Ep. to Timotheus Cap. 2. vers 1. 2. 3.</bibl>
                  <p>I exhort therfore, that firſt of all, ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thankes be made for all men: for Kinges, and for all that are in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that we may lead a quiet and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable life in all godlines and honeſtie.</p>
                  <p>For this is good, and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His exhortation (as alſo the whole epiſtle) was written and ſent by Paul the bleſſed Apoſtle of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to <note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1: 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Timothy</hi> the Euangeliſt, whom he beſought when he went to Macedonia, to abide at <hi>Epheſus</hi> a renowned city of <hi>Aſia,</hi> wherein the Lord had planted a famous <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev. 1. 11. and</hi> 2: 1.</note> Church of Saints and true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of his name, notwithſtanding the heatheniſh ſervice of that great god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe Diana and the image which fell downe from Iupiter did there ſo greatly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119628:12"/> flouriſh (Act. 19: 24. 27. 28. 35.) where the Lord wrought by the hands of Paul many miracles (Acts 19: 11.) where the Apoſtle fought with beaſts in the manner of men (1 Cor. 15: 32.) and wherein there was a great doore and effectuall opened to him, though there were manie adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, 1 Cor. 16: 9. The end of the abiding of Timothy at Epheſus in the Apoſtle his abſence, was to ſupply that ſervice which the Apoſtle himſelf ſhould have done if he had bin preſent, namely, <note n="a" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1: 3.</note> to charge ſome that they ſhould <hi>teach no other doctrine</hi> than that which the Apoſtle had taught them, or than was agreable to <note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1: 13.</note> 
               <hi>ſound and wholſome wordes of faith and love which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Now as perſons of greater place and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, leaving others more inferior in wiſdome and power, to diſcharge ſome duty for them in their neceſſary abſence (or to attend upon a ſervice which they themſelves are called from by occaſions elſwhere) doe give them not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, but alſo direction how the ſame ſhould be done: So the Apoſtle Paul (the maſter builder of the Churches of the gentiles, 1 Cor. 3: 10.) not onlie giveth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119628:12"/> Timothy commiſſion to tarry in his ſtead; but alſo counſelleth and directeth him how to behave himſelfe <hi>in the houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God, the pillar and ground of truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 3: 16. And amongſt the many moſt excellent, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, &amp; infallible rules of direction, which he giveth him, we are now called upon to conſider and attend unto one of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and principalleſt thinges w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he gave him in charge; the which he doth not in commanding and lordly termes, but with meekneſſe and love, ſaying, <hi>I exhort ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that firſt of all, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle's intent and purpoſe in this exhortation, is not to Timothy alone, that he ſhould performe this; but that he ſhould teach it to the Church of God, as the mynd of the Apoſtle, which was the <note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7: 40.</note> mynd of God himſelfe, wherfore the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>I exhort therfore, &amp;c.</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, If any man ſhall reſiſt or refuſe thy exhortation to, or example in the performance of this duty; let them know that it is the exhortation of me Paul the Apoſtle of Chriſt, who have with power and demonſtration of the Spirit approved my ſelf among them by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119628:13"/> ſignes and wonders to be no fabler or leight fellowe, to be no ſeducer and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull worker, but the miniſter, legate, and meſſenger of God himſelfe, who hath put his word in my mouth, which if they obey not, they may have cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent it.</p>
            <p>As this exhortation was at the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and penned by the Apoſtle, for the inſtruction of the church of God, and the ſubſtance of this treatiſe thereupon delivered to a congregation of Believers (as is noted in the preface) So the intent now of publiſhing it, is not to exhort wicked and worldly men to make prayers and ſupplications unto God, or to aſſure them of any benefit by ſo doeing; for the ſcripture ſaith that <hi>the ſacrifices of the wicked are abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 15: 8. and 21: 27. and 28: 9. <hi>and thoſe that call upon the name of the Lord shall be ſaved,</hi> but <hi>how shall they call upon him in whom they have not believed? &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 10: 13. 14. And if they ſay they doe believe, then the ſcripture ſaith againe, that <hi>faith without works is dead,</hi> Jam. 2: 17. 20. 26. and they that profeſſe they know God, and in <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1: 16.</note> workes deny him, and are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119628:13"/> and diſobedient, and unto every good worke reprobate; they have the <note n="e" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3: 5.</note> forme of godlineſſe, but denie the power thereof, and therfore we are bidden to turne away from them; (I ſhould rather exhort ſuch, to repent, and be converted that their ſins may be blotted out when the times of refreſhment ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, Acts. 3: 19. and then they may come with boldneſſe to the throne of grace, and be ſure to find grace to help in time of need, Heb. 4: 16. for they muſt be purged even as gold and ſilver, before they can offer to the Lord an offering in righteouſneſſe, Mal. 3: 3.) But my purpoſe in manifeſting this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, is partly to put the Church of God in mynd (as in duty and by calling I am bound) what is the beſt and moſt ſafeſt meanes to be uſed by them in theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous times, to helpe to allay the diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of our native Countrie; and that ſuch a meanes as whereby they (though abſent from them yet) may helpe them, &amp; that more effectually than if they ſhould run home and fight for them; to wit by their earneſt prayers, teares, and ſtrong cryes unto God, which prevaile powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119628:14"/> when ſword and ſpeare can doe no good: and partly (as hath bin before touched) to give the world and all judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious readers to underſtand (if they will underſtand anie thing) that thoſe faithfull Chriſtians which goe commonly (though falſely) under the name of Browniſts, are not ſo corrupt in doctrine and manners as hath bin (ſince the ſeſſion of this preſent Parliament of England) divers times in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated againſt them by perſons of no meane quality, whoſe wordes (by reaſon of their place &amp; dignity) doe call for credit when they affirme any thing inword or writing, and that not only ſuch as aſſiſt the King, but alſo ſome that ſeeme to plead for the Parliament as if Browniſts as they terme them were the only and chief foiſterers and fomentors of theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions, and the only maſterleſſe and unruly perſons in the common wealth, and ſuch as can not endure Kingly gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement or authority over them. And this I have attempted not for the credit of the perſons of the profeſſors (for they can have no greater credit and honour upon earth, than to be <hi>falſely accuſed for the name of Christ,</hi> Math. 5: 11. 12.) but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119628:14"/> for the truth's ſake, that ſuch as deſire or inclyne to the embraceing thereof, may receive no ſtumbling block or offence by theſe aſperſions, but maie <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1: 21.</note> 
               <hi>with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe receave the ingraffed word which is able to ſave their ſoules;</hi> and that they who have already receaved it may not ſo faint in their myndes, that they ſhould by theſe reprochfull ſlaunders be turned aſide from the good way whereunto the Lord hath called them; but have ſomething to anſwere thoſe that ſhall thus accuſe them; and by their perſeverance in well doeing put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men, and <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6: 9.</note> 
               <hi>never be weary of well doeing, knowing that in due time they shall reape, if they faint not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe verſes therfore and ſo forward<note place="margin">The ſcope.</note> unto the end of the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> vers of this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Apoſtle exhorteth to the carefull and diligent performance of publike prayers, wherein he teacheth, that we are not only to be myndfull of our ſelves, but ought to remember all men in our prayers to God, and eſpetially Kings and all other magiſtrates, of whom there might have bin then great occaſion to doubt whither they ſhould be prayed for or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119628:15"/> ſeing they were ſuch bitter enemyes to the Church of God. But for them eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially the Apoſtle proveth that Chriſtians ought to pray, by an argument drawen from the profitable effect which ſhould &amp; might come thereby to themſelves, viz that they (by their prayers ſeeking &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureing the ſafety &amp; preſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Kings and magiſtrates, &amp; their equall &amp; juſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their office) <hi>might live a pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable &amp; quiet life in all godlines &amp; honeſty.</hi> And for all men both kinges &amp; people, by an argument drawen from a certaine &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured effect which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but follow upon our faithfull &amp; ferve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prayers in this kind; viz that therein we ſhould pleaſe God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> How ever it goeth with us in reſpect of the King and people, though he continue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be a tyrant againſt us, &amp; regard not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> benefit which might come to him and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> land by the prayers of the faithfull, and they doe continue ſtill in their ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> refuſing of the knowledge of God: ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our praying for them ſhall returne into our owne boſomes, it ſhall not come home empty; for: 1: <hi>this is good,</hi> that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a greable to the will of God, profitable and benefitiall unto our ſelves. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> 
               <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119628:15"/> in the ſight of God our Saviour:</hi> A thing wherein he is much delighted as, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the ſweet incenſe and <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 14 1: 2:</note> evening ſacrifice. The which goodnes and acceptablenes of prayer the Apoſtle proveth by another ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, taken from the end whereunto God would have all men to attaine, which is ſalvation. Wherein we may appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Apoſtle's argument to be to this effect. He that willeth or is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the end, the ſame willeth alſo and is well pleaſed with the uſe of the lawfull meanes for attayning to that end: But God willeth all men, that is all ſortes of men aſwell Kings and other magiſtrates as people to be <note n="i" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3: 9.</note> ſaved: Therfore God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and it is a thing good and acceptable in his ſight that prayers and ſupplications be made for them that they may come to the knowledge of his truth &amp; ſo be ſaved. Vers 4. Now that God doth will the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all ſortes of men he confirmeth by a double reaſon, Vers 5. and 6. firſt becaus there is but one God of all ſorts of men, that is, becaus one and the ſame God hath choſen his people in &amp; out of every order and condition of men, whom he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to be objects of his favour. There
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119628:16"/> is not one God of the King, and an other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſubject; not one of the rich an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> another of the poore; not one of the <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3: 29.</note> Jew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and another of the gentile; but he only that juſtifieth both Jew and gentile, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> able to ſave both king and people; it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10: 12</note> 
               <hi>ſame Lord over all that is rich unto al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that call upon him;</hi> and he alone knoweth who are his, 2 Tim. 2: 19. Secondly becaus there is but one mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man, the man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who hath given and offered up him ſelfe to the father, as the price of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all thoſe whom the father hath given him out of every kindred and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and kingdome and people, out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every ſexe &amp; condition. Amongſt whom he putteth no difference, but alike dye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for them all, for there is <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3: 11.</note> neither gree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor Jew, circumciſſion nor uncircumciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Barbarian, Scythian, bond nor free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but Chriſt is all and in all, and all are one in him, whom the Lord will have to be teſtifyed in due time to his elect of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſorts and conditions, to the end that they might beleeve in him, and beleeving might have life through his name; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 15: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> 
               <hi>known unto God are all his workes from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119628:16"/> beginning of the world.</hi> Now prayer is an eſpetiall meanes whereby the word of this ſalvation is made <note n="o" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3: 1.</note> 
               <hi>to paſſe</hi> and take effect upon all and unto all whom God hath predeſtinated unto <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1: 5.</note> 
               <hi>adoption of children by Ieſus Chriſt unto himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good pleaſure of his will.</hi> So that this, to wit, the teſtifying of Jeſus Chriſt unto all, may be another argument to move us to pray for all.</p>
            <p>Or (if we would have the diviſion<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> ſhorter, and ſuch as we may more eaſily comprehend, then) thus we have it. Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the duties exhorted to, viz prayer and thankeſgiving. Secondly for whom theſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> duties are to be performed; not for our ſelves allone, but for all men of what eſtates or conditions ſoever, and if for all, then eſpetially for kings and thoſe in authority, becaus of the profit and peace which may come thereby to our ſelves, <hi>that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty.</hi> Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The argument to move us to the free and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eady performance of thoſe dutyes for all men, viz becaus <hi>it is good and acceptable in the ſight of God, &amp;c.</hi> as if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, whatſoever is good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119628:17"/> in the ſight of God, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ought to be carefull to doe and performe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> But to pray for all men, is good and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the ſight of God (how ever it go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> us, whither they perſecute us or giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us libertie) <hi>I Exhort therfore, that firſt of all ſupplications, prayers, Interceſſions, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of thankes, be made for all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before we come to the handling of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dutyes here mentioned, it ſhalbe worth our labour, to mynd the occaſion of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtle's putting Timothy in mynd o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe duties, and the manner how he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth them to him, wherein he is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> example or patterne to Timothy, how he ſhall commend this to the church o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God.</p>
            <p>The occaſion is conteyned in the illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive particle, therfore, <hi>I exhort therfore</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which calleth upon us, to looke back upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the matter or ſubſtance of the foregoeing chapter, eſpetiallie that which is ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> downe in the verſes imediatly goeing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this exhortation. Wherein th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtle remembereth Timothy of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dangerous condition of ſuch as <note n="n" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim. 1: 4. 5. 6. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>give hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to fables, &amp;c.</hi> of ſuch as <hi>ſwarved fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith, charity, and a good conſcience, turnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119628:17"/> aſide after vaine jangling, and diſputations about the law, &amp;c.</hi> and of the mercie of God ſhewed to himſelfe in particuler, in <hi>accounting him faithfull, and putting him into his ſervice who before was a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, &amp;c.</hi> And having concluded the occaſion of his writing this epiſtle with <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vers</hi> 17.</note> thankeſgiving to God, he proceedeth to give Timothy his generall charge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſheweth to what end he writeth this charge unto him, namely, that he <hi>by the peopheſies which were before of him might warre a good warfore, holding faith and a good conſcience,</hi> the which he ſhould have the more care of, for that he knew of ſome already that had <hi>made shipwrak of faith, of whom were Hymeneus and Alexander.</hi> From which generall charge the Apoſtle proceedeth to this firſt and principall duty to be obſerved by the Church, of which Timothy was to have care. So that in the former chapter the Apoſtle ſeemeth to make a generall enterance into this epiſtle, wherein he prepareth Timothy to receave his direction and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and now he begineth to handle the particuler thinges whereof he was to have a Care, as a faithfull miniſter of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119628:18"/> Chriſt. Of which the firſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall duty which he was to performe, and to ſee performed, or to exhort others unto, was to prayer, &amp;c. The two gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and more ordinary dutyes of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the goſpell are deſcribed Act. 6: 4. to be <hi>prayer and the miniſtrie of the word.</hi> Theſe are the thinges whereunto they are to give themſelves, as the Apoſtles in that place reſolved to doe for their parts; for indeed all thinges are <note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4: 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſanctifyed by the word of God &amp; prayer.</hi> The performance of theſe duties of piety prayer and thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, are eſpetiall meanes to confirme and keep us in the true and ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, to nouriſh and increaſe in us faith and a good conſcience, which ſome had put away, as the Apoſtle complaineth in the imediatly foregoeing verſes; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not in vaine, but to good purpoſe that the Apoſtle begineth firſt with this duty, ſaying, <hi>I exhort therfore that firſt of all ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As concerning the manner of the Apoſtle his laying downe theſe dutyes, it is not in any dominereing and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding way, with threatenings and loftie
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119628:18"/> termes or geſture (as the manner of Lordly prelates is to behave themſelves towards their clerkes) not as if the Apoſtle were Timothy's <note n="q" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1: 2.</note> father in the Lord, not as if Paul were an Apoſtle which was a chiefe office, and Timothy but an Euangeliſt which was more inferiour, but as if they were equals, fellow ſervants (as indeed the Apoſtle doth account the meaneſt mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt that ſerved with him in the worke of the Lord, Philem. Vers 1. 2. 1 Theſſ. 3: 2. Col. 4: 7. 11. Coloſſ. 1: 7. Philip. 2: 25. and 4: 3. 2 Cor. 8: 23.) for he ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>I exhort,</hi> beſeech, pray, and perſwade; or by the reaſons and arguments preceding, and following, I move, counſill, and ſtirre you up, as the word is diverſly rendered by our tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. In Rom. 15: 30. <hi>I beſeech you bretheren by our Lord Jeſus Christ, and by the love of the Spirit, that you help togither with me in your prayers, &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 12: 1. <hi>I beſeech you therfore brethren by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Cor. 6: 1. <hi>we beſeech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou alſo, &amp;c. 1 Tim. 6: 2. Theſe things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>each and exhort.</hi> Tit. 2: 6. <hi>Exhort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oung men to be ſober mynded, &amp;c.</hi> (See <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo, 1 Theſſ. 5: 11. 14.) that is, by ſound
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119628:19"/> and wholſome reaſons and arguments in doctrine perſwade and move them. Wherfore we ſhall find that the Apoſtle ſeldome or never uſeth this word exhort in his owne perſon to others, but he either prefixeth or affixeth reaſons to move the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the doeing of that which he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to them. And John the Baptiſt is ſaid when he preached to be <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 3: 18.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> exhorting, &amp; the Apoſtle calleth his owne doctrine <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2: 3.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> exhortation. Whence we may learne what are the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons that faithfull Biſhops and overſeers of the ſoules of God's people muſt uſe to provoke &amp; prick forward the flock com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge in the doeing of good dutyes, and to reſiſt and oppoſe ſuch as doe withſtand the truth; they muſt not be carnall and fleſhly weapons (of proceſſes, citations, injunctions, threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, impriſonings (take him purſivant, a dowtie argument to come out of a preacher's mouth) ſuch as have bin uſed by ſome who have called themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Biſhops but may be termed bad-ſhips o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> late yeares in their eccleſiaſticall (tyrani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call) courtes and conſiſtories) but they muſt be mighty through God pulling
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119628:19"/> downe the ſtrong holdes of Satan, <note n="r" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10: 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>caſting downe imaginations, and everie high thing that exalteth it ſelf against the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt;</hi> they muſt not be the cuſtomes of the Church, nor the lawes of the magiſtrate (much leſſe of a fewe corrupt men in lane ſleeves and fourſquared caps) that muſt be their ſheild and buckler, but it muſt be <hi>by</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1: 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſound doctrine</hi> that they muſt both <hi>exhort</hi> the one and <hi>gainſay</hi> the other; which muſt be produced out of that well ſpring of learning the holy Scripture, which is given by <note n="t" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3: 16. 17.</note> 
               <hi>in ſpiration of God and is</hi> (only and ſuffitiently) <hi>profitable for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſnes, that the man of God may be perfect throughly furnished unto all good works?</hi> For whoſoever <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8: 20.</note> ſpeaketh not according to the word which is written in the law and in the teſtimony, it is becaus there is no light in him; and whatſoever he be (though an Angell from heaven) that ſhall ſeeke to drawe us by any other doctrine or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments than what are learned thence, we may not hold him a miniſter of Chriſt,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119628:20"/> but an inſtrument of Satan <note n="x" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11: 15.</note> tranſformed into the likeneſſe of a miniſter of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, that he may deceave the better; and ſuch an one is pronounced to be <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</p>
            <p>Eraſmus noteth that Ambroſe an antient<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Annota: in locum fortaſſe legit</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> writer rendereth this word <hi>Exhortare</hi> in the imparative mood, and ſecond perſon, as if the Apoſtle would have Timothy exhort others viz the Church of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. Howſoever we take it, it ſtill ſerveth to ſhew what meeknes and care the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the goſpel ſhould uſe in directing the church of God in performance of her duty. Meekneſſe, in that it muſt not be with terror and maſterlynes; but with ſoft and gentle admonitions and exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Care, in that it muſt not be only in ſoft and ſtill words, but thoſe wordes muſt be ſound and forceable; wordes which muſt carry with them their force of argument. For it is not enough to ſpeak unto the church, but it muſt be to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, with underſtanding, uſing ſuch arguments and reaſons, as may convince the conſcience, and perſwade the heart (<hi>as the</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4: 11.</note> 
               <hi>oracles of God</hi>) to obedience, and take away all doubt and ſcruple which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119628:20"/> may any wiſe hinder from the doeing of the duty, or beleeving the doctrine. For, to lay one ſtone upon an other is not to build, that is but to heap up ſtones; but to fit the ſtone for his proper place, and to faſten it in with morter, that is the worke of building. So, they that edifie the Church muſt not doe it by heaping up wordes and ſpeeches (the <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10: 19.</note> multitude whereof doth darken <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi> 38: 2.</note> counſill, and therein iniquity can not be wanting) preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to this or that at randome (as it were) and confuſedly: but the exhortation being layd upon a good foundation (ſome ſolid and ſound doctrine or theſis of truth) muſt be fitted to it's proper place, and then be beaten in with the hammer or trowell of God's law, ſemented or faſtened in its place by ſuffitient arguments, drawen from the profit and benefit which ſhall accrew to them in the doeing of ſuch or ſuch a ſervice, and the loſſe and damage which cometh by the neglect thereof, and illuſtrated by examples and lively ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, whereby the ſame may be the more pleaſing and delightfull to the eye of the mynd. And this is to ſpeake a word to edification and exhortation. The like<note place="margin">b 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14: 3.</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119628:21"/> may be ſaid alſo of comfort, which is by wholſome and ſound wordes and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (drawen from the cauſes and ends of affliction, the grace and mercy of God, and the comfortable promiſes thereof which he hath made unto us in his word) to incourage thoſe that are in affliction and calamity to lift up their heades, and to have chearfull Spirits waiting patiently upon the Lord who ſhall give a good iſſue to all their adverſities. Whereof we have an exact preſident commended to us by the Apoſtle, Heb. 12. vers 1. &amp;c. vers 5. &amp;. vers 12. to the end. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our newe Engliſh tranſlation and the old latine render this ſame word in <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 1 Theſſ. 5: 11. <hi>Comfort your ſelves togither,</hi> which our old tranſlation in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and the newer tranſlations in latine expreſſe thus <hi>Exhort one an other.</hi> Which (if we approve of both) may give us to learne that true comforting is by ſound and godly exhortations, which muſt be framed as before.</p>
            <p>We may further obſerve (in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Apoſtle's laying downe this exhortation) the ſeaſon time or order of performing theſe dutyes <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>firſt of all</hi> or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119628:21"/> before all thinges. Some will have the genitive caſe (<hi>of all</hi>) to be referred to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications prayers, &amp;c, as if the Apoſtle did require the prayers of all the church to be made. Which I take rather to be a niceity in the interpretation (an humor which many men are troubled with, who would faine vent ſome conceits which others dream not of) than to have any appearance from the text ſeing the verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>be made</hi>) cometh betwene <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>of all</hi>) and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>ſupplications</hi>) whereas if the genitive caſe had agreed with <hi>ſupplications, &amp;c,</hi> it ſhould have bin ſet either imediatly before or after it and the other. Yet (notwithſtanding this wreſted interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be not approved of) I take the Apoſtles meaning to be, that all the church ſhould performe thoſe dutyes as hath bin declared in the generall ſcope. Others will have theſe wordes <hi>first of all</hi> to be underſtood according to Chriſt's precept <hi>first ſeeke the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, &amp;c.</hi> Math. 6: 33, not ſo much to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the order of time as the dignity of the thing to be performed. Which under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding either of the wordes of Chriſt or of the Apoſtle I can not take to be the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119628:22"/> moſt currant or ſtricteſt, though in ſome ſort I ſhould grant, that God doth not ſo much eſteem the firſt performance of a thing in reſpect of the outward order or circumſtance of time, as that it ſhould have the firſt and principall ſeat in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and deſires of our hearts: yet I can not withall but mynd, that what the heart doth moſt principally &amp; earneſtly deſire, that the tongue will preferre to the firſt place in the outward expreſſion, for our Saviour ſaith that <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 12: 34.</note> 
               <hi>out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi> And ſurely if our hearts did moſt of all in ſincerity <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5: 6.</note> 
               <hi>hunger and thirſt after righteouſnes,</hi> and our affections were not ſet on things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low but on thinges in <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3: 1, 2.</note> heaven, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prayers and petitions would in the firſt place tend to that purpoſe, according to that perfect platforme which Chriſt hath <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 6: 9. &amp;c.</note> taught us, wherein he hath ſet the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which imediatly concerne God and his glory, before thoſe which doe mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nerely concerne our ſelves. And for my part, I dare not in any caſe have a though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to queſtion the perfection of that form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of prayer, either in ſubſtance or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; though yet I doe not intend to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119628:22"/> put a bond upon the Spirits of the Saints, without the obſervation whereof their prayers can be no way acceptable. But I feare, leaſt our preferring (in our forme of prayers) the praying for the forgivenes of ſin and Gods grace and bleſſing to be poured downe upon us in particuler, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſeeking of the ſanctifying of his name, the doeing of his will, and coming of his Kingdome, doe not proceed out of a ſelf-love, and greater deſire we have of our owne ſalvation, than of Gods glory ſimply.</p>
            <p>Therfore in ſimplicity, if we take theſe wordes to be the Apoſtles exhortation (which is the agreement of moſt interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the beſt gramaticall conſtruction of the word exhort, as appeareth by the uſe thereof in other places) then I can not but conceave his intent to be, not only to note the dignity of theſe dutyes, but alſo the very order of performance, that they ſhould be done in the firſt place, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other thinges. And indeed the Apoſtles (who had as little need to pray as any, being not prone to erre in their doctrines) doe place it firſt in order of their miniſteriall adminiſtrations viz
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119628:23"/>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 6: 4.</note> 
               <hi>prayer and miniſtery of the word:</hi> and if we conſider well the worthines and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of this dutie, it ſhall not only have the preferment in our thoughts, but alſo in our practice. Wherfore I conclude hence, that it is an approved &amp; laudable practiſe which the Churches of the Saints have learned, and doe uſe, and good it is that they ſhould continue the reverent obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation thereof, namely, that before they enter into the adminiſtration of the word of God, they make prayers ſupplications, inrerceſſions, and giving of thankes to God. For indeed it is by prayer, that we procure helpe and aſſiſtance to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter, heare, and underſtand the word. Prayer and thankeſgiving ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be the firſt and laſt, the beginning and end, the opening and ſhutting up of every Chriſtian aſſembly. Begin there with, that we may have help to performe the worke we are taking in hand. End therewith that we may have that accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and bleſſed, that hath bin done.</p>
            <p>And if ſuch be the carriage of Gods people in their coming togither before God, then may they confidently expect to have him that walketh <hi>in the</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 2: 1.</note> 
               <hi>midst
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119628:23"/> of the ſeven golden candleſticks,</hi> and <hi>hath the ſeven ſtarres in his right hand</hi> to be with them, for he hath ſaid <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 18: 20.</note> 
               <hi>where two or three are met togither in my name there am I in the midſt of them:</hi> and the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth ſaying, <hi>whither ye eat or drinke or whatſoever ye doe, doe all to the glory of God, 1 Cor.</hi> 10: 31. and againe, <hi>whatſoever ye doe in word or deed, doe all in the name of the Lord Ieſus, giving thanks to God and the father by him Coloſ.</hi> 3: 17.</p>
            <p>Here the church of God may (by the way) further take notice of a point worthy of conſideration; namely that if prayers and thankeſgiving be ſuch principall, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and worthy dutyes to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in their publike aſſemblies, then they ought to take care when they elect any to miniſter the word unto them, that they be ſuch as are endued with the Spirit of ſupplication alſo, and that in no leſſe a meaſure than with the Spirit of propheſie; and that becaus theſe are the chiefeſt and principall duties: and indeed when men have well and effectually performed this duty, a good half of the worke is done; and there is no doubt that ſeing prayer and miniſtrie of the word are the moſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119628:24"/> and frequent adminiſtrations of this kind of church-officers, that whom the Lord hath fitted for the one, is alſo endued with ability to performe the other. And therfore hereby may be ſeen the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thoſe people, that have admitted thoſe to be thruſt upon them, as curates of their ſoules, who though they have made ſhift, now and then, to tickle them with an homilie, or (it may be) to pronounce a long ſtudyed for ſermon, yet have bin no way able to poure out upon all occaſions prayers and thankeſgiving to God, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than out of a booke, or a ſtinted forme which they have with much a doe collected togither, and learned without booke, which they have uſed as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon hackney in their devotion.</p>
            <p>If we take theſe words as ſpoken to Timothy, that he ſhould exhort, &amp;c. then we muſt underſtand that theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des <hi>firſt of all,</hi> doe commend unto him the dignitie and neceſſity of theſe dutyes; and it will ſerve to informe us, that the doctrines concerning prayer and thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving are ſuch, as ſhould be upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions taught in the Church, and the people of God be earneſtly exhorted to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119628:24"/> the practiſe of them, and that as princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and eſpetiall duties to be by them performed. Yea and if we mynd the Apoſtle's omitting to ſet downe any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler perſons, whom he doth exhort (though it be before in the entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymated that he intendeth principally the Church of Epheſus, yet naming none) he ſheweth that neither Timothy the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt to whom he writeth this epiſtle, nor the Church in generall, nor any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iculer member thereof, high or lowe, rich or poore, learned or unlearned, but were obliged to, and had need to be exerciſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n theſe manifeſtations of their faith and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove, as thinges well pleaſing to God, and profitable to themſelves. Therfore I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ope that none will thinke this an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy thing that I have now taken in hand, which is in theſe times of trouble wherein iniquity doth abound and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove of many doth waxe cold, and there are not only two, but many yea a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omber who like <hi>Hymeneus and Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> have put away faith and a good conſcience, and concerning faith have made Shipwrack) to ſtirre up <note n="l" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3: 1.</note> 
               <hi>the pure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yndes</hi> of God's people, to the diligent
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119628:25"/> and carefull performance of ſupplication and prayers unto God, which is the ſureſt and powerfulleſt meanes which can be uſed by us for the obtayning of an happie iſſue of all theſe diſtractions; for ſaith the Pſalmiſt <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.</note> 
               <hi>then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he delivereth them out of their diſtreſſes:</hi> the rather becaus the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion of our aſſembling doth call upon us for ſuch meditations, for we are met togither this day to ſeeke the face of the Lord in the behalf of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves and the people among whom we ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journe, and with whom the Lord hath made us partakers of many great delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances from the handes of their and our enemyes, and with whom we are ſtill in danger of them, their feare is our feare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their diſtreſſe ours, their deliverance and preſervation ours; and amongſt them thoſe that are in authority being the chiefe pilots (under God) who doe guide the helme or rudder of this our common wealth. Thoſe that goe before us i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fighting the battailes of the Country abroad, and keeping peace at home, by their well ordered governement, if they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cut off our ſhip is like to be expoſed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119628:25"/> great danger, if not ſhipwrack: wherfore we have great reaſon to pray if for all men, then eſpetially for them. To which purpoſe tend theſe wordes of the Apoſtle (which I have thought alſo to ſuite well with our preſent occaſion) ſaying <hi>I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort therfore that first of all ſupplications prayers interceſſions and giving of thanks be made for all men: for kings, and for all that are in authority, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſomme and ſubſtance of which wordes is to exhort us to <hi>prayer and thankeſgiving,</hi> as we have heard before. In the laying downe of which two duties the Apoſtle uſeth foure ſeverall wordes as if they were ſo many ſeverall duties to be performed; as firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Supplications</hi> which ſome tranſlate obſecrations or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations, that is prayers againſt evill or for deliverance from evills. Secondly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>prayers,</hi> which are by ſome tranſlated, orations, petitions; that is cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or deſiring ſome good thing to be beſtowed on us. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſions,</hi> which ſome take to meane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints we make of thoſe that hurt us, but then it ſhould be rather rendered inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ellations: others take interceſſions in this
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119628:26"/> place to be for the turning of the hearts of our perſecutors; but moſt agree in this that they doe ſignifie the requeſts or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires which we make unto God one for another, whither of the firſt or ſecond kind which ſeemeth to be the cleareſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of this word ſeing it is uſed Rom. 8: 34. Heb. 7: 25. where the text giveth the direct &amp; ſimple meaning of it. Others make this diſtinction, that by the firſt word is meant all kind of prayers in generall; the ſecond, when ſome certaine thing is deſired; and by the third is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied prayers made for others. All to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither then thus, humble and earneſt ſeekings unto God, for any bleſſing ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall or temporall, for our ſelves or others, or deliverance from any danger to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not dare to trace the pathes of curious ſpeculations about the etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of theſe wordes and the diſtinction of prayers into ſeverall kinds and ſortes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in this place; but rather take the Apoſtles ſcope and purpoſe to be in theſe different expreſſions both to ſet downe a perfect generall rule, which ſhould containe in it all particulers, that thereou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119628:26"/> might be no ſtarting hole for any unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table mynd, to warrant the omiſſion of any kind of prayer for the perſons herein after mentioned; and alſo to preſſe us earneſtly to the performance of this duty. The which freedome and fulneſſe of ſpeech the Apoſtle uſeth in other places when he ſaith Epheſ. 6: 18. <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>praying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with all</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>prayer and</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſupplication, and watching therunto with all perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſupplication for all Saints:</hi> and Philip. 4: 6. <hi>Be carefull for no thing: but in every thing by prayer and ſupplication with thankeſgiving, let your requeſt be made knowen unto God.</hi> And this I inclyne unto the rather for that in the hebrew text of the old teſtament I find ſeverall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des uſed by the holy Ghoſt for theſe thinges; yet he doth not intend any cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious or neceſſary diſtinction, but a more earneſt and plentifull expreſſion, the more to ſet out the excellency and perfection of his owne ſcripture. For I find the word <hi>Thepilah</hi> in 2 Cron. 6: 29. tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>prayers</hi> which word hath its deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Paalal</hi> to judge, appeaſe, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermine cauſes, for which appeales are made. See Pſal. 106: 30. Sometime
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119628:27"/> to conclude by thought and imagination upon ſome ground induceing the mynd thereunto, as Gen. 48: 11. <hi>I had not thought to ſee, &amp;c.</hi> yet the holy Ghoſt doth not thereby make any ſtrict diſtinction, for in 1 Sam. 2: 25. (<hi>If one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyn againſt an other, the Gods shall</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pilelo.</note> 
               <hi>judge him: but if a man ſin against God, who</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palel-lo.</note> 
               <hi>shall intreat for him</hi>) there it may be rendered <hi>intercede,</hi> or <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate.</hi> So like wiſe in 2 Cron. 30: 18. <hi>But Hezekiah prayed for them,</hi> that is, interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for them, &amp;c. And in Jſa. 1: 15. <hi>when you make many</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilah.</note> 
               <hi>prayers, I will not heare,</hi> there it is not taken diſtinctly for any one kind or ſort of prayers, but generally all of what kind ſoever. So alſo I find <hi>Thechinoh</hi> (which cometh of <hi>Chaanan</hi> with ſignifieth to doe a thing gratis Jud. 21: 22. Pro. 26: 25. &amp; is uſed to ſet forth the free grace &amp; meere good will of God, Exod. 33: 19.) in 2 Cron. 6: 29. and 1 King. 8: 33. tranſlated <hi>Supplications,</hi> ſo alſo in Heſt. 4: 8. Job 8: 5. Pſal. 30: 8. and 142: 1. Jſa. 45: 14. 1 King. 8: 59. and <hi>intreatyes</hi> Pro. 18: 23. Job 19: 17, which is an earneſt ſeeking of the face: but by 1 King. 8: 30, I find that the holy Ghoſt intendeth no curious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction by this from the firſt phraſe, for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119628:27"/> there it is ſaid thus, <hi>And heare thou the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of thy ſervant, &amp; thy people Iſrael, which they shall</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Iithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pale-lu.</note> 
               <hi>pray in this place;</hi> where both the words are indifferenlty uſed, for they are ſaid to pray their ſupplications: And in 2 Cron. 33: 13. it is ſaid of Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeh the king of Judah, that in his affliction he humbled himſelf greatly before the God of his fathers, <hi>And prayed unto him, &amp; he was intreated of him &amp; heard his ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, &amp;c.</hi> where both the former words are alſo indifferently uſed, for his prayer is called ſupplication. So alſo in the 1 King. 9: 3. the Lord ſaid unto Solomon, <hi>I have heard thy prayer and thy ſupplication which thou haſt made, &amp;c.</hi> in Heb. which <note n="v" place="margin">Hithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thah.</note> 
               <hi>thou haſt ſupplicated;</hi> where he is ſaid to have ſupplicated his prayer as well as his ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. The like maybe ſaid of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Iſa. 53: 12. which is tranſlated <hi>will make interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> See Jer. 36: 25. Iſa. 36: 25. Iſa. 59: 16. it cometh of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifieth properly (as the learned note) to meet, or run upon one, to fall upon one, Gen. 32: 1. Judg. 8: 21. Iſa. 53: 6. the Lord hath laid on him, &amp;c. Heb. the Lord hath cauſed our ſins to run upon him, like a ſwift ſtreame or flood runing from an hill into an hole
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119628:28"/> or pit in the bottome (if I may believe my author) and by a metaphor, to run or ſtep in betweene, to intercede, to ſtep forth either with the body or wordes to mediate or make interceſſion, according to which it is uſed in Jer. 27: 18. <hi>let them run</hi> (or make interceſſion) <hi>to the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> Gen. 23: 8. but according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of the word it may ſignifie any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing of our ſelves unto the Lord as it is uſed, Job 21: 15. <hi>if we pray unto him,</hi> there it can not be (properly) interceſſion. Wherfore to confirme and ratifie this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition we ſhall find in Jer. 7: 16. divers wordes indifferently uſed to one and the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Pray not thou for this people, neither lift up</hi> 
               <note n="v" place="margin">Rinah of Ranan to cry out for ſorrovv or joy.</note> 
               <hi>cry, not</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Thepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah.</note> 
               <hi>prayer for them, neither make</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>interceſſion to me, &amp;c.</hi> By all which termes the Lord intendeth no other but to ſtay Jeremy from becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an interceſſor for the people. But enough of this.</p>
            <p>The three wordes hitherto ſpoken of, tend only to the ſetting forth of the firſt duty here exhorted unto; the ſecond duty is commended to us in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> phraſe onlie, which is <hi>giving of thankes,</hi> that is a thankfull acknowledgement unto God
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119628:28"/> Almightie (who is the giver of every good and perfect giving) for the delivering of men from evill, or for anie bleſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on them. It is a thankfull retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, or rendering againe unto God of la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and praiſe both with heart and voice for his benefits beſtowed upon us o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> others. It is called in Scripture the <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116: 13.</note> 
               <hi>cup of Salvation,</hi> and the <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14: 2.</note> 
               <hi>calves of our lips,</hi> which <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13: 15.</note> in and through Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our mediator and Redeemer (being offered upon that golden altare) are more acceptable unto God than all <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50: 8. 14.</note> burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and ſacrifices.</p>
            <p>Prayer and thankeſgiving, is either private, when a man poureth out his ſoule in ſecret unto God, Math. 6: 5. 1. Tim. 2: 8. or publike, in the Congregation of the Saints, with the church and people of God. They are not here reſtrayned to either of the two in particuler (though the Apoſtle doth principally intend the publike performance of them, as hath bin before touched) therfore it followeth that both kindes are included in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. Whence ariſeth this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,<note place="margin">Doctrine. Neceſsity of prayer and thanks.</note> viz That prayer and thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to God, are dutyes neceſſary to be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119628:29"/> performed at all times, and by all degrees of perſons in the Church of Chriſt. They are here the firſt and principall dutyes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to by the Apoſtle. As for prayer wich is the firſt here mentioned God hath <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> commanded us to call upon him Pſal. 50: 15. and in the performance of this duty is he in a principall manner worſhipped by his Saints, which is the ſubſtance of the firſt table of his law. Our Saviour <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Chriſt, and his Apoſtles have commended it as a duty to be performed by us, and that at all times and ſeaſons Math. 7: 7. Luk. 18: 1. Math. 26: 41. Epheſ. 6: 18. 1 Theſ. 5: 17. 1 Pet. 4: 7. And who is there that would not make much of the performance of a duty enjoyned by ſuch worthy patrones? If our earthly prince command us by his Herald of armes, or proclamation, to performe ſome great ſervice, we would uſe all meanes to ſet about it, leaſt we ſhould by our neglect fall into danger: howe much more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and expedient that we ſhould care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerve to doe this duty which is commanded us by <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19: 16.</note> 
               <hi>King of Kings and Lord of Lords,</hi> by him who is <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nom.</hi> 27: 16.</note> 
               <hi>God of the Spirits of all flesh,</hi> in whom we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119628:29"/>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 17: 28.</note> 
               <hi>live move and have our being,</hi> who is the <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1: 17.</note> 
               <hi>father of lights from whome cometh every good and perfect giving,</hi> who can <hi>give us richly all</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6: 17.</note> 
               <hi>thinges to enioy,</hi> and hath promiſed to give us <note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5: 14.</note> whatſoever we aſk according to his will. Our manyfold wants and neceſſities doe call upon us with all earneſtneſſe, yea require us to be myndfull of this duty. We have an heavy yoke and unſupportable burthen lying upon us, which without his mercy and compaſſion will preſſe us downe to Hell, namely, the guilt and pollution of originall ſin, that deformity and depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of nature, which we brought into the world with us, from the loynes of our firſt parents; for we were <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51: 5.</note> 
               <hi>borne in ſin and conceaved in iniquitie,</hi> and <hi>by</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2: 3.</note> 
               <hi>nature we are the children of wrath as well as others,</hi> by which we are become ſo defective and unprofitable that we are <hi>not</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3: 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſuffitient of our ſelves</hi> ſo much as <hi>to thinke a good thought,</hi> much leſſe to doe any good deed; for though we have ſometimes a deſire or will to doe that which is good, yet <hi>we can not finde how to</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7: 18.</note> 
               <hi>performe the ſame,</hi> when we would doe good evill is preſent with us: And this yoke and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119628:30"/> can be no wiſe taken off our necks, or we any wayes eaſed of the ſame, but of the aboundant grace of God, in and through the merits of our Saviour Chriſt, which wee then feele to have obtained when we have receaved <hi>the Spirit of</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 12: 10.</note> 
               <hi>grace and ſupplication,</hi> by whoſe effectuall ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in our hearts we are imboldened and inabled with penitent hearts and full aſſurance of faith to goe unto his throne of grace and pray ſaying, <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6: 12.</note> 
               <hi>forgive us our ſins as we forgive them that treſpaſſe againſt us.</hi> We are in continuall perrills and feares both from without and within our ſelves, Our hearts <hi>are deceitfull and</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 17: 9.</note> 
               <hi>wicked above all thinges, who can beare them?</hi> our fleſh is ſo weake it is no way able to reſiſt, yea it is rather ready and inclyning to <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1: 14.</note> tempt and draw us unto maniefold inconveniences. Our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary the Divell is alwayes buſied <hi>as a</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5: 8.</note> 
               <hi>roaring lyon walking about</hi> with us whitherſoever we goe, or whatſoever we doe, <hi>ſeeking</hi> all occaſions and oppertuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>to devoure us,</hi> deſirours <hi>to ſift us as</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22: 31.</note> 
               <hi>wheat is ſifted</hi> with a ſive, to rob us of whatſoever good thing we have, if it be poſſible; and we <hi>are</hi> 
               <note n="v" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2: 11.</note> 
               <hi>not ignorant of his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119628:30"/> diviſes,</hi> what a craftie, deep, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile polititian he is, <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2: 24.</note> full of enterprizes, and baites which he layeth to catch us, as the <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 9: 12.</note> ſilly fiſh is caught in the net, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times tranſforming himſelf into an <note n="z" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11: 14.</note> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of light, as he did to our firſt parents, making them believe that they ſhould be <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3: 5.</note> as Gods, that he ſought nothing but their good; and as he did unto our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt himſelf, he aſſaulted him with a ſentence of <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4: 6.</note> Scripture, as if he ſought to perſwade him to no thing, but that which was agreable to the will of God, when indeed he is <hi>a</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8: 44.</note> 
               <hi>lyer and the father of lyes:</hi> like unto whom are his miniſters, they can turne themſelves into the ſhape of the <note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11: 15.</note> miniſters of Chriſt, making the ſimple believe that prelaticall Epiſcopacie is of divine right; that the worſhip of God is not pure and holy, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be performed in a conſecrated church or chappell; nor the Supper of the Lord reverently receaved, unleſſe the piece of bread be adored by proſtrating of the body before it; that we honor not the name of our Saviour, unleſſe we bow the knee, or put off the cap, whenſoever we heare the name of Jeſus (whereby
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119628:31"/> many ignorant ones (it may be) ſometimes miſtake <note n="*" place="margin">VVhere the Apocrypha is allovved to be read in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</note> Jeſus the ſon of Syrach, or Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus called Juſtus, or <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 7: 45.</note> Jeſus who brought in the Iſraelites into the poſſeſſion of the gentiles, for Jeſus our Saviour who is the ſon of God) and many other thinges which are comonly taught by his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, yea and uſhered in with manie quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of ſcripture and fathers, as if their doctrines and phantaſies were Oracles of God, undenyable truths; when indeed they are no thing but error, and falſhood, the very <note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4: 1.</note> 
               <hi>doctrine of divels,</hi> Idol ſervice and <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2: 18.</note> 
               <hi>will worship,</hi> according to the <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2: 8.</note> 
               <hi>traditions of men and not after Chriſt.</hi> Againſt whoſe ſubtilties and craftie devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where with they <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4: 14.</note> lye in wait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave we are no way able to reſiſt, unleſſe the Lord of his meere grace in Chriſt doe give unto us <hi>the Spirit</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16: 13.</note> 
               <hi>of truth,</hi> by whom we may be led into all truth, and made to diſcerne between good &amp; evill &amp; cleave to that which is good and forſake that which is evill, the which <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 11: 13.</note> holy Spirit he hath promiſed to give to thoſe that aſke him. Behold then what great neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity we have every one of us to pray night and day unto God for his helpe and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119628:31"/> againſt this our deadly enemie, for we <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6: 12.</note> wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood but againſt principalities and powers, yea Spirituall wickedneſſes that are in high places; wherfore we ſhall find that the Apoſtle adviſeth us to the practiſe hereof as a maine weapon to <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6: 18.</note> reſiſt the fiery darts of the Divell, that having done all thinges we may ſtand <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph</hi> 6: 13.</note> faſt in the faith. And our Saviour comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth us <hi>to</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26: 41.</note> 
               <hi>watoh and praie,</hi> that we enter not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Every day bringeth with it evill <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6: 34.</note> ſuffitient for the day, whereby we are incombred with maniefold neceſſityes, for we have not food or rayment of our ſelves, no not the leaſt health, ſtrength, or ability of body, by our owne wiſdome; it is God that <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136: 25.</note> 
               <hi>giveth food to all flesh,</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6: 28 29. 30.</note> that clotheth the lillyes and feedeth the ravens when they cry, whoſe is <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24: 1.</note> the earth and the fulneſſe thereof, whoſe <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10: 22.</note> bleſſing it is that maketh rich, and he addeth no ſorrow with it, without whom all our labour toyle and induſtrie is but as water ſpilt upon the ground, for <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 127: 1.</note> 
               <hi>he build the houſe the worke-man worketh but in vaine, except he keepe the city the watch-man waketh but in vaine:</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119628:32"/> wherfore we can never have aſſurance to have theſe our bodily wants ſupplyed from day to day, unleſſe we be carefull to ſeeke it of God by prayer, as our Saviour hath taught us ſaying <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6: 11.</note> 
               <hi>give us this day our daylie bread.</hi> And if I ſhould here inſiſt upon the dangerous times in which we live, and the daylie feares where with we are incompaſſed, now that we heare of warres and rumors of warrs in all quarters and parts of the earth, now that the ſtroake is come even to our doores, our native Country (which hath bin famous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned amongſt all nations for traffique and manufacture by ſea and land, mightie in conqueſts, famous for riches and learning, ſurpaſſing others in the light of the goſpell, which was more or leſſe ſpread abroad over the whole Kingdome) lyeth here and there weltring in the bloud of her owne ſlaine; and we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall talke and diſcourſe of the great nomber of bloodly enemyes that are among us, as ſo many Serpents in our owne boſomes, ready to bite and devoure us: it might be a ſuffitient and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full argument to be produced for the proofe of this point to ſhew the neceſſity
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119628:32"/> offervent fervent and faithfull prayers to be pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out to the God of hoſts whoſe <hi>name is a</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 18: 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrong tower whereto the righteous run and are ſafe;</hi> but I feare to darken counſell by a multitude of wordes without knowledge, I know our owne hearts and dayly thoughts can not but preſſe this home unto us with greater ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie than I can ſpeake it. And who is there that is now ſo ſottiſh or ſenceleſſe, as not to mynd, that if ever, now are the times wherein the Saints are <hi>to come often</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3: 16.</note> 
               <hi>togither,</hi> (and every one in his <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 12: 12.</note> houſe and cloſet a part) to poure out ſtrong cries and teares unto him that is able to make us overcome all difficulties, for <hi>if God be with us</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118: 6</note> 
               <hi>we need not feare what man can doe unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 23.</note> goe downe to the ſea in ſhips, and occupie in the deepe waters, they well know how needfull an anchor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to a ſhip; for it is one of the principall implements which they are carefull to preſerve: So may prayer be ſaid to be to the ſoule of every true Chriſtian; for it will helpe to beget and worke in us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ope, which is the <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> anchor of the ſoule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth ſure and ſtedfaſt and it entereth into
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119628:33"/> that within the vaile, where Chriſt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> high prieſt ſitteth at the right hand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God. And as a key is neceſſary for the opening of a doore that is faſt locked: So is prayer neceſſary to open the ſhut doore of our heart, to open the doore of <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 14: 27.</note> faith unro us, to open the doore of <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 4: 3.</note> utterance unto us, yea the doore of heaven it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereby we may have entrance unto the throne of grace, <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4: 16.</note> to aſke grace to help in time of need. Wherfore a learne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doctor calleth the juſt man's prayer <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Oratio juſti clavis eſt coeli, aſcendit precatio &amp; deſcendit Dei miſericerdia. Aug. ſer. de tom.</hi> 226.</note> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> key of heaven, becaus it aſcending up to God draweth downe his mercy upon us.</p>
            <p>The reverent and faithfull perfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mance of this duty is a note whereby w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may know the Saints of the moſt high; &amp; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> whereby we ſhall approve our ſelves to our owne conſciences in the ſight of God 1 Cor. 1: 2, whereas the wicked are bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the not doeing of it Pſal. 14: 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Job 21: 14. 15.</p>
            <p>The frequent performance is alſo very <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> profitable. 1. To procure favour an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mercy from God. 2. To preſerve it. 3. To regaine any good loſt. and fourthly to turne away anie judgement plague, or trouble, whither generally o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119628:33"/> the ſtate wherein we live, or of the church whereof we are members, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly of our ſelves; for the Lord hath promiſed us helpe and deliverance herein if we will but call upon him, for he ſaith <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50: 15.</note> 
               <hi>Call upon me in the time of trouble, and I will deliver thee, and thou shalt glorifie me.</hi> Is the judgment or affliction already upon us, be it a common calamity, as the ſword, captivity, plague, famine or the like, or particuler chaſtiſement, as ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, baniſhment, povertie, diſtreſſe &amp;c? See what pregnant proofes we have in Scripture of the validity of prayer in ſuch caſes. When the King of Aſſyria had ſent rayling <note n="l" place="margin">2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Rabshekeh</hi> to revyle the people of God, and good king <hi>Heſekiah;</hi> and to threaten warre againſt them: <hi>Heſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> went into the houſe of the Lord, and prayed unto him with earneſt affection; and the Lord did not only deſtroy in one night an hundred foureſkore and five thouſand of the King of Aſſyria's hoſt; but alſo ſhortly after the king himſelf was ſlaine &amp; that by his owne ſons. Wee have read what captivitie and bondage the children of Iſrael were in under <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Aegipt</hi> and his people: yet the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119628:34"/> Lord heard the <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3: 7.</note> prayers of his people, and of his ſervants <hi>Moſes and Aaron;</hi> and brought them out from thence, with a ſtrong hand and out ſtretched arme; and ſo did he alſo afterwards deliver them from many other ſervitudes wherein they were. <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> was for his idolatry taken priſoner by the hoſt of the King of Aſſhur, and they put him in fetters, bound him with chaines, and carryed him away captive into Babel: and when he was there in tribulation, <note n="n" place="margin">2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 23: 12. 13.</note> he prayed to the Lord his God, and humbled himſelf greatly before the God of his fathers; and God was intreated of him, and heard his prayer, and brought him againe to Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem into his kingdome. When the peſtilence was inflicted ſo ſore upon the people of Iſrael, as that there dyed in three dayes ſeventie thouſand perſons; <hi>King David</hi> raiſed an altar unto the Lord and offered <note n="o" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam. 24. Laſt.</hi>
               </note> burnt offerings and peac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offerings: and the Lord was appeaſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the land, and the plague ceaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from Iſrael. <note n="p" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 20: 3. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Heſekiah</hi> when he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſick, he turned his back to the wall an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prayed, and wept ſore; and he receave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſently a meſſage from the Lord, by
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119628:34"/> the mouth of Iſaiah the prophet, that his life ſhould be prolonged, and he ſhould recover. And the Apoſtle James aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth us that <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 5: 15.</note> 
               <hi>prayer of faith shall ſave the ſick.</hi> Yea prayer is a ſpeciall remedy for the ſicknes of the ſoule which is the <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 15: 15.</note> greateſt ſicknes that we can be afflicted withall in this life.</p>
            <p>Is the judgment or affliction not yet fallen upon a people, but threatened gainſt them as it is againſt us at this day if we repent not? let us know then that prayer (if it be fervent) is an eſpetiall meanes, a ſoveraigne remedie to avert and turne away the ſame. A proofe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we have in the people of <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionah.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Niniveh</hi> unto whom though the Lord ſent his prophet with an expreſſe meſſage to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his judgment againſt them for their ſins, telling them directly (as if there had bin no recalling it) yet fortie dayes and Niniveh ſhalbe deſtroyed: yet the people of Niniveh beleeving God, and humbling themſelves with faſting and crying mightily unto the Lord; the text ſaith that <hi>the Lord heard them and repented him of the evill which he had threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened againſt them. Iacob</hi> hereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119628:35"/> with God when he was <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32: 7. 9. 28.</note> in feare of his brother Eſau: and ſo may we too, if we pray with faith and waver not.</p>
            <p>Which ſerveth both to reprove the too <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> too great neglect of this holy duty; and to exhort and ſtirre us up to the diligent and zealous practiſe thereof. It is one of the greateſt charges wich lyeth upon the miniſters of the goſpell, to teach men how to pray, and to preſſe them to the doeing of it; there being not a more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſigne that a man is the child of God than this that he hath receaved the Spirit of grace whereby he is made able willing and ready to goe unto God as his father; and with true faith and fervencie of ſpirit to poure out his complaints and ſupplications to him as his preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion requireth. Art thou then by diſtance of place, impriſonment, baniſhment, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary travaile, or otherwiſe, removed from the ordinarie hearing of the word of God taught and preached; from fanctifying the Lord's day, in doeing the publick duties of worſhip and ſervice unto thy maker with the reſt of thy bretheren the people of God, and thyne heart doth as it were long and pant (as the hart doth for <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42: 1.</note> the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119628:35"/> brooks of water) to appeare before God in thoſe his publike ordinances and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations? be not diſcomforted: but alwayes have recourſe unto God in prayer, <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6: 10.</note> three times a day with Daniel, <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119: 164.</note> ſeven times a day with David, alwayes as our bleſſed <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 18: 1.</note> Savior teacheth, and <note n="a" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5: 17.</note> continually as the Apoſtle Paul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth us, and above or before all thinges as we learne in the text. Offer up this ſacrifice to God morning and evening, ſaying with the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 14 1: 2.</note> 
               <hi>let my prayer aſcend unto thee as incenſe, and the lifting up of my hands as the evening ſacrifice.</hi> Let it be thy firſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt worke every day. Make it even the key to open the daie, and the lock to ſhut up the night, that thou mayeſt reſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>afety, and thy ſleep may be ſweet, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one may make thee affraid. Let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erformance hereof goe before they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eipt of thy daylie food, and conclude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he receipt thereof with giving God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raiſe: So ſhall the good creatures of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſanctified to thee. In a word, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oever thou goeſt about or layeſt thine and unto, though thou haſt not time or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pportunity ſolemnely upon thy knees
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119628:36"/> to utter a prayer in wordes, yet learne of <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2: 4.</note> 
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to lift up thine heart unto God.</p>
            <p>Art thou aſſaulted by Satan, or his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; and by him or them tempted to anie evill? praie to God to give thee ſtrength that thou be not <hi>led into</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6: 13.</note> 
               <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> but mayſt reſiſt and over come: and if thou receave it not at the firſt, leave not off, but pray with Paul <note n="e" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12: 8.</note> 
               <hi>the ſecond &amp; third time.</hi> Haſt thou yeilded and given way in any reſpect to the inticement of the fleſh, and art ſo farre overcome that thou haſt don evill and ſinned againſt thy God? Deſpaire not yet; but pray unto God to give thee repentance, that thou mayſt have aſſurance of the pardon of thy ſins, &amp; reconciliation to thy God. Doeſt thou find in thy ſelf upon examination of thy conſcience, that thou haſt deſerved God's judgments for thy ſins; and that they hang over thyne head, ready to be powred downe upon thee? pray unto God that he would take away thy ſins that are the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious cauſe of thoſe judgments; &amp; if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be his good pleaſure to remove the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo from thee. Hath God after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> long time of thy living in ſin and wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119628:36"/> found thee out though thou thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy ſelf ſure enough, deluding thy ſelf in thine owne heart, ſaying <hi>tush</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8: 12.</note> 
               <hi>God ſeeth not, &amp;c?</hi> and hath he layd his ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand upon thee to bring thee home to himſelf? humble thy ſelf under the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hand of God, rip up thine heart, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thy inward parts, conſider thy life paſt, confeſſe thy ſins, and pray earneſtly for deliverance, either by removall of the judgment, or leſſening it; or to give thee ſtrength and patience to beare and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe whatſoever he ſhall lay upon thee.</p>
            <p>As for the duty of thankeſgiving, if we<note place="margin">Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</note> performe not that, we are in danger to loſe the good, which we have gotten; neither can wee be ſure to obtaine any other thing we are in need of. Thankes is the ſacrifice which God requireth of us, and the end wherfore he beſtoweth his bleſſinges upon us Pſal. 50: 15. Therfore be thankfull. Much more might be ſpoken of the neceſſity, profit, and uſe of prayer, and to urge us to the frequent performance thereof: but I thinke that there is no one ſubject or point of doctrine, whereupon ſo much hath bin, and is continually ſpoken, and written,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119628:37"/> as on this; therfore all that I can ſpeake will be but a caſting of water into the ſea; and a long detayning you without ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient cauſe. There is none that have truly learned Chriſt, but are continually ſo ſencible thereof, that they are able in their owne hearts to comment largely upon this principle. Yet thus much I have ſpoken for the preſent neceſſity, ayming not ſo much to inſtruct, as to quicken and ſtirre up the mynds of the godly, to a zealous delight in approaching neare unto God, who is <hi>a liberall</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11: 6.</note> 
               <hi>rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of thoſe that ſeek him.</hi> And as for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of thankes I could well be contented to inſiſt more largely upon that alſo, the rather for the provoking of our ſelves, who doe enjoy ſingular bleſſings in a ſtrange land by the goodnes of our God, who moveth the Magiſtrates and people of the ſame to ſhew favour to us notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our ſins have incurred both his and their diſpleaſure. But ſomething remayning in the text yet untouched (unto which I haſten all that may be) doth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me, and it would aſke much time to handle every point at large.</p>
            <p>The next particuler in this exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119628:37"/> worthy of our conſideration is for whom the Apoſtle would have prayers and thankeſgiving to be made; and that is not for our ſelves only, but alſo for others, both thoſe that are with us, and farre from us, whither freinds or foes.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour Chriſt and his Apoſtles<note place="margin">To pray and give thanks for others.</note> doe commend unto us in many places the loveing of our neighbor Math. 22: 39. Joh. 15: 12. 1 Joh. 2: 9. 10. 11. and by the parable of the good <note n="h" place="margin">Luc. 10: 30. &amp;c.</note> Samaritane he ſheweth whom we are to repute our neighbor. Now as our neighborhood extendeth not only to them that are neare but alſo farre off unto all men: So the duty of love is manifeſt not in one, or ſome, but in all good thinges. Therfore pray for all, which are the very words of the Apoſtle <hi>I exhort therfore that first of all ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of thanks be made for all men.</hi> And this is to be done in no degree or manner leſſe and weaker than for our ſelves; but with the ſame fervencie love and earneſtneſſe, eſteeming their wants and neceſſities as our owne: for we know not but they may be of the ſame body with us, though for the preſent the condition of ſome may
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119628:38"/> ſeem otherwiſe. Wherfore we may not thinke it ſtrange that we are commanded to pray for all men, both good and bad, godly and wicked. The wickeder they ſeem to be (ſo long as they are not paſt hope) the more need they have of our prayers, that if it be the will of God they may be amended, that ſome change or reformation may be wrought in them. This point is plainly proved by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and practiſe of our Saviour Chriſt, who hath taught us to <hi>pray for our</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4: 44.</note> 
               <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, thoſe that cruelly perſecute us;</hi> and if for them then no queſtion, but we ſhould pray and give thanks for others. But maie <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> ſome ſay, we find ſome reſtraint in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of praying for all men without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. Sometimes God hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den it for ſome Jer. 11: 14. 1 Joh. 5: 16. Sometimes the Saints have bin ſo far from praying for perſons, that they have even prayed againſt them 2 Tim. 4: 14. and the prophet David in many places of his pſalmes. And our Saviour excepteth ſome out of his prayers Joh. 17: 9. To <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſvv. </seg>
               </label> which I anſwere, that theſe are ſpetiall caſes which muſt be excepted from this generall rule. As firſt thoſe in Jeremy
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119628:38"/> their hearts were obdurate in their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and God had manifeſted to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that he would without faile ſend his Iudgement upon them. Wherfore he forewarneth his prophet not to pray for their deliverance whom he had purpoſed to deſtroy. So if God doe by his ſpetiall word (as he did the prophet) forbid us to pray for ſuch and ſuch a people; who ſhall dare to pray for them? or what hope can he have to be heard? The Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in his law that man ſhall not <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20: 30.</note> kill his neighbour, and <hi>he that sheddeth mans blood by</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9: 6.</note> 
               <hi>man shall his blood be shed:</hi> but if God command <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22: 2.</note> Abraham to ſlay his ſon Iſaac, he muſt doe it, and ſhall have praiſe for ſo doeing. The ſecond place is of ſuch as have committed that great ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, of which there is no pardon to be obtayned Math. 12: 32. In ſuch a caſe though wee cry never ſo much for his forgivenes; yet the Lord will not heare us. As for the Saints praying againſt ſome, we muſt note that they were ſuch as they have had ſpetiall information of them by the motion of the Spirit, that they deſerved to be prayed againſt. And for that of our Saviour
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119628:39"/> Chriſt that he ſaith <hi>I pray for them</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his elect) <hi>and not for the world,,</hi> that is the wicked reprobates, we muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that ſpeech with vers 11. where our Saviour noteth what it is he ſeeketh for them, namely to keep them through his owne name that they might be one as the father and ſon are one, &amp;c. Now to pray thus for the wicked and damned hypocrites, which are only knowen to God, were a plaine reſiſting of his will and labor in vaine. For to what purpoſe ſhould we ſeeke ſalvation and eternall life to them who are ordayned unto eternall deſtruction from the preſence of God and the glory of his power? To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe were it for us to ſeeke the converſion of thoſe that have nothing to doe to <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50: 16.</note> take the ordinances of God in their lips becaus they hate to be reformed? But thoſe things being ſecret are only knowen unto God, and we being ignorant who it is by name that is reprobate and who not, but knowen unto God are all his workes: we are therfore to followe his revealed will, which <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29: 29.</note> 
               <hi>belongeth unto us and to our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and therein we are taught to pray for all men, that is, for all ſortes, eſtates,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119628:39"/> and conditions of men, high and low, rich and poore, Kings and ſubjects, Jewes and gentiles; and that becaus God will have all men to be ſaved and to come to the knowledge of his truth. That this is the meaning of this word the ſcripture other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where teacheth, Mat. 4: 23. Luc. 11: 42. Eph, 1: 3. 1 Cor. 10: 25.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle uſeth a generall terme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus it might containe and include all particulers, <hi>Exceptis excipiendis;</hi> and teaching us thus much, that there is no condition or degree of men whatſoever whom we may or can conſcionably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude or debarre from having benefit by our prayers, ſo long as they doe not (as Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian the Apoſtate) manifeſt a reſolute and malitious forſaking of God and reſiſting of his truth. So long as men are in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, though their malice ſeeme to be great, and their wicked zeale outragious; yet there is hope for ought we know, and therfore we muſt not deſiſt the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of our love, in ſeeking the ſalvation of their ſoules, or any other good they ſtand in need of. Wherfore let us put in practiſe this duty according to the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle's exhortation. God ſheweth himſelf
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119628:40"/> to be <hi>no</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 10: 34.</note> 
               <hi>reſpecter of perſons,</hi> nor to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18: 32.</note> the death of him that dyeth; but hath offered the manifeſtation of his grace to all: let us then imitate God herein, by offering up our prayers and thanks for all, as occaſion doth require. And in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer <hi>for Kinges and thoſe that are in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, &amp;c</hi> which is the 3d point here commended by the Apoſtle, to wit, the perſons whom in an eſpetiall manner we are bound to pray for. What the Apoſtle Paul meaneth here by <hi>Kings and all that are in authoritie is</hi> expounded by the Apoſtle Peter in theſe wordes <note n="r" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2: 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>whither it be to the King, as ſupreame; or unto gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, as unto them that are ſent by him, &amp;c.</hi> By <hi>King</hi> then the Apoſtle intendeth the ſupream and chief magiſtrate of the land where wee live; and by all that are in authoritie, he meaneth all other civile of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, into whoſe hand the ſword of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or any power of goverment, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or deputed, according to lawe. Under which is comprehended all civile parliaments, counſels, Judges, juſtices, Majors, baylifs, and whatſoever other courts, or perſons, they be, that are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly appointed, and ſet, for to rule or
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119628:40"/> governe the Kingdome, Countrie, city, ſhire, or corporation in which we inhabite. From whence this note ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth clearly; That it is the duty of every<note place="margin">Doctrine. Chriſtians are to pray for the civile gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors.</note> true Chriſtian both in his publike and private prayers to commend unto God all perſons that are in civile authority in the Common wealth, both ſuperiour and inferiour, both King and other magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. And good reaſon too, for the very <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> titles which the Apoſtle here giveth unto <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> them calleth for it. For kings he uſeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſome learned in the greek tongue interpret as if he were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <note n="*" place="margin">Therfore Kings should be the ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers of their people.</note> baſis or foundation of the people, being he that excelleth among the mortall rulers of this world: wherefore Chriſt is called <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17: 14.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> King of Kings, becaus he is above all the Kings and princes of the earth; and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall ſtand, when all theirs have an end, and they themſelves are become like other men, their honour being layd in the duſt; for <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1: 33.</note> 
               <hi>he shall raigne over the houſe of Iacob for ever; and of his kingdome there shalbe none end.</hi> It cometh of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifieth to raigne, to be in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to be a King, to beare rule and ſway,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119628:41"/> to be governor of, to beare a great or chief ſtroke in a matter or thing. In latine they are called <hi>Reges</hi> of <hi>rego</hi> to governe or rule, upon which title or denomination Eleutherius bb: of Rome writeth thus (if my <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts and mon. Pa. 96. Col.</hi> 2.</note> author faile me not) unto Lucius king of Brittaine about the yere 169. viz <hi>A King hath his name of ruling, and not of having a realme. Ye shalbe a King while ye rule well, but if you doe otherwiſe the name of a King shall not remaine with you, and you shall looſe it, which God forbid. The Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God grant you ſo to rule the realme of Brittaine, that you may raigne with him for ever whoſe vicar you be in the realme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word which is here uſed for thoſe in authority ſignifieth <hi>thoſe that are ſet in excelencyes,</hi> high dignities, or prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nences, to goe before others, or to have charge of others. All which ſerveth to ſhew that lawfull civile governors of what name or title ſoever, are ſet in great place and authority, and our prayers to God for them may doe much in helping them in the adminiſtration of their charge and governement.</p>
            <p>Secondly they are miniſters of God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:119628:41"/> for the good of thoſe that doe well, and to execute wrath upon him that doth evill;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> wherfore they ſtand in need of our prayers that God would fill them with wiſdome and underſtanding, to diſcerne between good &amp; evill, between right &amp; wrong; to adminiſter juſtice to the oppreſſed, &amp; to puniſh the oppreſſor; that they may know their obedient and loving ſubjects, from proud &amp; traiterous rebels, for <note n="*" place="margin">Virgil:</note> 
               <hi>Regûm eſt parcere ſubject is and debellare ſuperbos,</hi> it is the property of Kings to ſpare their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but to ſuppreſſe the proud and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious. And as they are the miniſters of God; ſo their office &amp; power is the ordinance of God, he hath appointed that there ſhalbe<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13: 1. 2.</note> governors &amp; rulers over the people; &amp; in his power it is, to ſet up and pull downe whom he pleaſeth. From whence it may he reaſoned thus, whatſoever function or adminiſtration is ordained and appointed of God, (whither it be for the good of the body or ſoul of man or both) whoſoever ſhalbe lawfully called to the executing of any ſuch charge, are to be prayed for, and thankes to be given to God for their good, or the good which we receave by them: But Kings and thoſe that are put
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119628:42"/> into lawfull place, are ſo ordained and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God; &amp; therfore to be prayed for &amp;c in obedience to Gods ordinance, and that it may be ſanctifyed unto us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly the burthen of all the civile <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſtate lyeth principally on their ſhoulders, and their miſcarriage tendeth to the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and hurt of the whole body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and ſo unto Chriſtians as they are members of the Comon wealth as well as others, as we may ſee by daylie expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. On the other hand, the ſafety, preſervation, and good carriage of the King reacheth unto the whole common wealth. What can be then leſſe done for them, than to commend them and their governement to God in our prayers, ſaying <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 72: 1.</note> 
               <hi>Give the King thy judgment ô Lord and thy righteouſnes to the Kings ſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly they are appointed of God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> (amongſt other things) for the maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his church and truth, againſt the perſecuting hands of malitious &amp; bloody enemyes: therfore neceſſary it is, yea the duty of every member of the Church, to pray for them; that the Lord would make them <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49: 23.</note> 
               <hi>nurſſing fathers to his Iſrael.</hi> For <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 21: 1.</note> 
               <hi>hearts of Kings are in the handes of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119628:42"/> the Lord; and as the rivers of water he turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them whither ſoever it pleaſeth him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, how ever it come to paſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> whither they be friends or enemyes, good or bad, for us or againſt us: yet in praying for them, we pleaſe God; and our prayers returne into our owne boſomes, as hath bin before noted.</p>
            <p>Which may ſerve for the juſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> of thoſe that in ſtead of praying for Kinges, princes, and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; doe curſe them, that is, ſpeake evill of them. Neither doe they beare that honour and reverence in their hearts to them which is meet, Exod. 22: 28. Eccl. 10: 20. 2 Pet. 2: 10. 11. Jude vers 8. And the equality and truth of this point may be a ground of exhortation to all that feare God to manifeſt their honour love and fidelity to their prince by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him. What though he be not ſo wiſe and prudent in governing, as he ought? yet let not that put thee off from performance of thy duty, which God hath required of thee. He ſhall anſwere for his adminiſtration; and thou for thy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and fidelity. His negligence ſhall not excuſe thee for thine. What
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119628:43"/> though he be an enemy to the truth, and ſeeketh to deſtroy thy body and goods, becaus thou canſt not with good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience obey his humane lawes, which thou findeſt to be contrarie to God's law? yet ceaſe not to pray for him, yea know, that in ſuch caſe thou haſt greater reaſon to pray for him; that God would turne his heart. And what knoweſt thou, but thy fervent prayers may prevaile ſo farr with God, as to move him to inclyne his heart, to ſhew favour to his people, and to ſuffer the truth to flouriſh; or at leaſt to favour thee in thy particuler. We have the comfortable experience here in this land, of God's power in this kind; witnes our feedome of the goſpell which we here enjoy, farre otherwiſe than ever any of our fathers could obtaine in our native Countrie (the more is the pity, the Lord lay it not to their charge) and can not the ſame God worke the ſame in the hearts of other princes and magiſtrates? doubtles his hand is not ſhorter in one place, than another; but for ought thou knoweſt, it is becaus thou art ſlack and negligent in calling upon God to powre his Spirit upon thy prince, and to give the Senators
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119628:43"/> wiſdome, and inclyne their hearts to ſhew pitie to his heritage. Beſides, is the King or the magiſtrate an enemy to thee? take heed how therfore thou ſeekeſt to <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12: 19.</note> 
               <hi>avenge thy ſelf</hi> of him by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding thy prayers from him: for this is diſpleaſing to him who hath commanded thee to <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5: 44.</note> 
               <hi>love thyne enemyes, bleſſe them that curſe thee, doe good to them that hate thee, and pray for them which deſpite fully uſe thee and perſecute thee.</hi> If ever the Chriſtian people of the Engliſh nation ſtood in need to be ſtirred up or awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this kind, now is the time; for me thinkes I heare divers complaine of the diſtance and diſcord which is between the Kings majeſtie, and the honourable Court of parliament; and the unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of the malignants, whom the King ſeemeth to countenance; and I heare di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and that religious people too, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaning the parliament and blaming the King: yea preparation is made of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of warre, and that by religious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the forwardeſt and moſt godlie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſhew their zeal in helping the parliament with men and mony: and I heare alſo of faſting and prayer for the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119628:44"/> good of the land and preſervation of the parliament; but I heare few or none of the better ſort utter good deſires concerning the King (though I can not but think that they intend the King with his parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as neceſſary adjuncts) and all becaus they take him now to be miſled &amp; carryed out of the way by wicked counſell. Is it ſo that the King ſeemeth to be led aſide from the way of Juſtice, and (it maie be unwittingly to his majeſty) runing upon the rocks of perill and poverty, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding the whole kingdome thereby? what great cauſe is there then for the faithfull, to lift up ſtrong cryes unto God, to confound and turne to fooliſhnes the counſels of the <note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15: 31.</note> 
               <hi>Achitophels,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the wicked from the throne of the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 25: 5.</note> King, and ſo over rule and perſwade the heart of the King, that as a father he may tender the lives &amp; eſtates of his children, his ſubjects, and as a prince of God, may ſo adminiſter the affaires of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that peace and truth may kiſſe each other; that ſuch as profeſſe to feare that great name of God may under him <hi>lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſtie</hi> which is the fourth particular
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119628:44"/> conſiderable in this exhortation, and the laſt point which I ſhalbe able at this time to handle, as the end wherfore Chriſtians are bound to pray for thoſe in authority; or the good fruit which we may by God's bleſſing reape, if we be not ſparing in ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the powerfull ſeed of our prayers for them. In which clauſe as there is plainly ſet downe a ſuffitient argument to enduce us to pray for Kings &amp;c: So there ſeemeth to be included what is the duty of magiſtrates in the common wealth, or where to God hath ordained them, and what he requireth of them, viz to ſee to the maintainance of: 1: peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. 2. godlines and 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> honeſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace</hi> is the profit and increaſe of the<note place="margin">Duty of princes.</note> common wealth, whereas warre is the overthrow and ruine of it; as may be ſeen in great kingdomes and Countries, which have bin utterly waſted, and depopulated, by having the ſeat of warre within their borders. So that there is great reaſon, that thoſe in ſupream authority, ſhould have a care to preſerve peace; for in ſo doeing they preſerve their owne, and the Country's riches, and ſafety. Happie therfore and renowned among men is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119628:45"/> that King or ſupreame magiſtrate who beareth not only in his Chreſt, but alſo in his breaſt this divine Mottoe <hi>Bleſſed are</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5: 9.</note> 
               <hi>the peacemakers:</hi> but ſad thoughts can not but be of thoſe princes, who like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall and hard hearted parents, ſhall not only with dry cheeks behold their children (their ſubjects) ſheathing their ſwords in each others bowels; but alſo countenance and defend the ringleaders and abettors of ſuch bloodie enterprizes. Surely ſuch (if ſuch there be) are farre from being ſons of peace. Should not the ſhedding of their owne blood touch them, and make them withdraw their hand? yea doubtles; otherwiſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray themſelves, to be unfit to governe; for <hi>he that ruleth over men muſt be just:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23: 3.</note> but how farr ſuch demeanour is from Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, a tender capacitie may ſoone deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Civile peace</hi> is alſo the tranquillity of the Churches of the Saints, who in the dayes of reſt and quiet doe flouriſh as a green baytree in the garden of God, ſpread abroad over nations and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; but in the daies of trouble and perſecution is driven into the wildernes
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119628:45"/> to hide herſelf from the rage of the wicked; where yet the Lord nouriſheth her &amp; maketh her to yeild her ſavour like the Camemal; which the more it is troden upon and depreſſed, the ſweeter ſmell it ſendeth forth. In the daies of peace and quietnes the people of God ſit under their vines and figtrees, eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and making melodie in their hearts unto God; flocking (like doves to their windowes, like Eagles to the carkaſe) in multitudes to the celebration of God's ordinances. Whereas the times of trouble and perſecution make them to ſit downe in mourning and hang by their harpes, as not able <hi>to</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.</note> 
               <hi>ſing the ſong of Sion;</hi> but remembring the Lord a farre off, as one that turneth his back upon them; which maketh them to ſigh and groan and to cloth themſelves in ſackcloth, and to have aſhes for their meat, and mingle their wine with weeping. Their meetings togither then (if at all) are in feare and ſorrowe, ſtil looking for their enemy to come upon them, to make a prey of their lives. Let then every true Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like heart never ceaſe praying for Kings and thoſe in authority that under them
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119628:46"/> we may live <hi>a peaceable and quiet life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> is the pillar of the common wealth: for where that is cheriſhed, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, and maintayned, by the higher powers; that kingdom is doubtleſſe ſtable and firme, and ſo ſhall continue. For there is neither treacherie or rebellion at home, or open invaſion from abroad, that ſhall anie way diſtract that prince who maketh the Lord his hope, and ſerveth him continually: nor hurt that people that walke in his feare.</p>
            <p>Wherfore it is a principall thing which God requireth in princes, that they be men <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18: 21. 22.</note> 
               <hi>fearing God,</hi> and the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael ſaith, that they muſt <note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23: 3.</note> 
               <hi>rule in the feare of God.</hi> I can not here omit ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that I have lately read written by one <note n="*" place="margin">Ioſua de la Cave.</note> of our times in an Epiſtle to the ſtates of Holland and Weſt-Friſia, to this effect, <note n="e" place="margin">Vbi religio est locum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent bonae le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ac bona diſciplina, ex quibus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunati feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſque even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionibus praecipu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis naſcuntur: ſieut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contra etiam ſublata religione corruere rempub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licam oportet: quonia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſublata Dei timore ſequitur impietas, &amp; ruins Imperiorum.</note> where religion is, good lawes and good diſcipline have place; by which come proſperous and happie events eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially in warlike expeditions: as on the contrary religion being taken away, the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119628:46"/> common wealth muſt faile: becaus when the feare of God is taken away ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines followeth, and the ruine of Empires. And againe, <note n="*" place="margin">Duo fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damenta t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tius bonae ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietatis ſunt religio &amp; Iuſtitia, ubi c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptum ab illis declinari, &amp; pro mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulo minuitur felicitas Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae: ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos rebellare in ſe ſentit or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinario Iure, qui Deo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellis eſt.</note> Religion and Juſtice are the two only props of a good ſociety: when once men begin to declyne from them, the happines alſo of the common wealth doth diminiſh: he ordinarily feeleth the rebellion of his ſubjects againſt him, that is himſelf a rebell againſt God. And afterwards <note n="‡" place="margin">Cum pura manet religio, tum bene or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinata ſtat politia, &amp; a Deo conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vata incolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</note> when Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth pure, then the civile ſtate is well ordered, &amp; is kept in ſafety by God. Now princes may be ſaid to maintaine godlines, firſt by aboliſhing and rooting out of their kingdome (as much as in them is) all falſe wayes, invented and feigned religions, all Idols, and ſuperſtitious vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But if they be on the other hand ſeekers to root out godlines and the feare of God from among them, by perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Saints, forbiding preaching, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Idol-ſervice; tollerating the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming of the name of God, and breach of his ſabaths; they ſhall never be able to hold up their heads, when the King of Kings ſhall call them to an accompt. Secondly, by upholding and maintayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119628:47"/> the true Chriſtian religion, defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Churches of Chriſt from the abuſing hands and tongues of wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors. But if they themſelves be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of the godly, reſtrayning them of their liberty of publike ſervice of God, inflicting fines, amercements, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and other corporall puniſhments, upon men that make conſcience of the way of Gods ſervice, &amp; the true religion: what will they ſay when God ſhall viſite their iniquity with a rod, &amp; their ſin with ſcourges?</p>
            <p>This is the principall charge and duty of princes, if they did but know their duty; namely to further the honour of God, and his worſhip and ſervice. Firſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becaus it is from him they have their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice &amp; charge; they are his miniſters; they could have no power <hi>except it were given them from above:</hi> and therfore good reaſon that they ſhould uſe it principally in the furtherance of godlineſſe. See Dan. 2: 21. 37. Pro. 8: 15. Joh. 19: 11. Ezek. 29. 19. 20. Rom. 13: 1. 2. 3. 4. Jerem. 27: 8. Secondly, God hath honoured them, with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> giving them his title, <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 82: 1. 2 Cron. 19: 6.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119628:47"/> therfore it is their ſhame if they ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhonour him; which they doe if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeke not by all lawfull wayes and meanes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he promotion of his worſhip and ſervice. Thirdly this appeareth by the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of Almightie God, in all ages ſince we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead of Kinges ruling upon Earth, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the land of Judah, and alſo in Iſrael, and others Countries: in that he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erved thoſe that have feared him and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>romoted godlineſſe (though but in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mall meaſure) whereas he hath deſtroyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cut off their name and memoriall that have rebelled againſt him, and bin abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors of Idolatry, and falſe worſhip, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t have bin but in the forme and manner of his ſervice (which amongſt men is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted an indifferent thing, but it is not ſo with God, who will have his will to be the only law to rule in mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences) as he did the Kinges of Iſrael, who maintayned the calves at <hi>Dan and Bethel,</hi> which Jeroboam the ſon of Nebat had ſet up. And how did he plague Pharaoh and all Aegipt, for that they would not <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5: 1.</note> ſuffer the childeren of Iſrael to goe and doe ſervice to their God, as he had commanded them? which example
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119628:48"/> (me thinketh) were alone enough to make the hearts of all Kings, princes, and magiſtrates, be they of ſupreame, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior authority, to tremble and quake; who know that hiſtorie of God's fearful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> judgments upon that king and people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet are guilty of the ſame ſin; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they will not ſuffer the people of God, to <note n="f" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6: 17.</note> ſeperate from their Idolatries, and to ſerve the Lord upon the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev. 14: 1. VVith Zach.</hi> 2: 7.</note> Mount Sion where he hath commanded to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by his Saints. They will hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Saints of God, the holy ones of the moſt high, to pollute themſelves wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Aegyptian Idols, to hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with their Babyloniſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, and to approve and juſtifie them yea to accompanie with them in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull works of darknes, Idol-ſervice, and Image worſhip; or els fire and fagot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> halter and gibbet, ſword and perſecutio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall follow them: yea and ſuch new kinds of torture, as never before theſe evill dayes have bin heard to have bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inflicted upon the Saints, as if men for conſcience towards God were to be notcht &amp; cut or mark'd like dogs, rogues, or open perjured varlets. If this be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:119628:48"/> a great oppreſſion of the poore weakling, and a depriving the free borne ſubject of his liberty, (nay his liberty of conſcience which is more deare than life) and making them ſlaves and vaſſals to mens wills and malitious practiſes, whither right or wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, I am ignorant what is: whereas man being a reaſonable creature, and having a ſpirit of wiſdome and underſtanding given him from the Almightie, ſhould be governed by rationall lawes, grounded upon the law of God, &amp; light of nature; and when he is found after due conviction to be a rebell then is it time enough to puniſh him: but if a man be able with meeknes and feare any wiſe to manifeſt, that that which is put upon him, is contrary to the word of God, and he can not doe this without ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt God, and the ſcripture ſaith <hi>it is better to obey God than man;</hi> then to compell ſuch a man to doe any thing againſt the check of his conſcience, or to puniſh him for not doeing it, or for doeing the good which is contrary thereunto, is not ruling but tyranie. Oh that now at length the <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 10. 11. 12.</note> Kings of the earth would be wiſe! and that the Judges and rulers of the world would by that and ſuch like
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119628:49"/> examples learne to <hi>ſerve the Lord in feare, and rejoyce in trembling!</hi> Oh that they would themſelves and their people with them, caſt off that affinitie which they have made with that Arch-enemy of Chriſt the man of ſin; and would <hi>kiſſe the ſon leaſt he be angry, and they perish in the way when his wrath shall ſuddainly burne,</hi> and none ſhall quench it! for it is the will of God <hi>that</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5: 23.</note> 
               <hi>all men should honour the ſon as they honor the father: he that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth not the ſon, honoureth not the father, which hath ſent him.</hi> But is it ſo that they will not honour the ſon by ſubmitting themſelves, their crownes and ſcepters at <hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">i</hi>
               </hi> his feet, to ſerve him<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev</hi> 21: 24.</note> and his church by being nurſing fathers unto his people (Iſa. 49: 23. and 60: 10.) if they will not <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 22. 3.</note> 
               <hi>execute Iudgment and righteouſnes, and deliver the oppreſſed from the hand of the oppreſſor, and vexe not the ſtranger, the fatherleſſe or the widowe: but will doe violence and shed innocent blood?</hi> will they not ſet before them the law of the Lord God of heaven, &amp; <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut. 17: vers</hi> 18. 19. 20.</note> read there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and learne thereby to feare the Lord God whoſe name is <hi>Iehovah,</hi> and keep all the wordes of his law to doe them; but
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119628:49"/> will have their hearts lift up above their bretheren, and will oppreſſe them and make them ſubmit to their humane lawes and ordinances, which they have them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſucked out of the poyſoned cup of fornications in the hand of that great whore, that rideth upon that ſcarlet beaſt, whoſe name is a <hi>a Mysterie, great Babilon, the mother of whoredomes, and abominations of the earth; and will</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17: 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>have one mynd, and give their power and authority to the beast,</hi> and all, to fight againſt the lambe, and thoſe that are with him, who are called and choſen and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: Then let them know that if they turne not ſudainly, he that is <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19: 11. 12. 13. 14. 15. 16.</note> faithfull and true, who judgeth and warreth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, whoſe eies are a flame of fire, and on whoſe head are many crownes, whoſe name is <hi>THE WORD OF GOD,</hi> who hath a companie of warriers fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him upon white horſes, clothed with fine lynnen white and pure, out of whoſe mouth goeth a two-edged ſword wherewith he ſmiteth the nations; who is the king of kings and Lord of Lords, and hath all <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28: 18</note> power given him both in heaven and earth: that he (I ſay)
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119628:50"/> hath <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſol.</hi> 7: 12.</note> bent his bow and made his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes ready to ſhoot at thoſe wicked perſecutors; and ſudainly will he ſpeake unto them in his wrath &amp; vexe them in his ſore diſpleaſure. Then ſhall they be ſlaine with the <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19: 18: 21.</note> ſword of him that ſitteth upon the horſe, which (ſword) cometh out of his mouth; and their fleſh ſhalbe given for meat to the foules of heaven. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the Lord did for Iſrael his people, how he avenged the wrong that was offered or done unto them by the princes and nations of the earth; how he overthrew Pharaoh and his hoſt in the red ſea, he ſmote <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 136: 15.</note> great Kings and ſlew famous kings, Sihon King of the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, and Og the King of Baſhan, and gave their land for an heritage unto Iſrael his ſervant; yea he ſuffered no <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105: 14. 15.</note> man to doe them wrong, but reproved Kings for their ſakes, ſaying <hi>touch not myne anointed nor doe my prophets no harme.</hi> Who ever hath fought againſt God and prevailed? it is <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 9: 5.</note> 
               <hi>hard to kick against the pricks:</hi> now they that moleſt and perſecute the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, fight againſt and reſiſt <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 9: 4.</note> Chriſt; for they that touch them touch the <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 2: 8.</note> apple of his eye, and pretious in the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119628:50"/> ſight of the Lord is <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 116: 15.</note> the death of his Saints. Therfore let them not thinke to uphold themſelves by their preſent power and dignitie, which they doe enjoy, as if there were no poſſibilitie to prevaile againſt them: but let them conſider with feare and reverence, that he <hi>by whom</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 8: 15.</note> 
               <hi>Kings raigne and princes decree juſtice,</hi> who lifteth and <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4: 25.</note> ſetteth up Kings, &amp; pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them downe againe at his pleaſure, can turne the hearts of their nobles and people againſt them, and make them be caſt out (like <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4: 33.</note> Nebucchadnezar) to eate graſſe with the beaſts of the field, till they know that the moſt high ruleth the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the earth. Yea, when they ſhall ſay peace, peace (pleaſing themſelves in their wickednes, and making ſure, to them ſelves the bringing to paſſe of their purpoſes) <hi>then</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5: 3</note> 
               <hi>shall come upon them ſudaine deſtruction, as travaile upon a woman with child, and they shall not eſcape.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Honeſty.</hi> This is the honour and ſafety of a common wealth. The ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſins of the heathens were the cauſes, wherfore their lands did ſpew out both them and their princes. Therfore it can
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119628:51"/> not but be an eſpetiall duty of Kinges and all that are in authority, by the ſword of juſtice committed to them, to cut downe ſin and iniquity; that it be not ſuffered, much leſſe maintained, in their dominions: For ſin and iniquitie abounding is the caus wherfore the Lord doth bring great and terrible judgments upon the nations of the earth. <hi>A fruitfull land</hi> (ſaith the <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 107: 34.</note> pſalmiſt) <hi>becometh barraynnes for the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the people that dwell therein.</hi> And this doubtleſſe is the controverſy which the Lord hath at preſent with the Inhabitants of England, <hi>becaus there is no</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4: 1. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>truth, nor mercie, nor knowledge of God in the land, but by ſwearing &amp; lying, &amp; killing &amp; ſtealing &amp; committing adultery, they break out &amp; blood toucheth blood:</hi> Therfore ſhall the land mourne, &amp; every one that dwelleth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhall languiſh, with the beaſts of the field &amp; with the fowles of heaven, yea the fiſhes of the ſea alſo ſhalbe taken away. Whereas the rooting out of wickednes and vice, and the maintaynance of true religion and virtue, hath bin, is, and ſhall be an eſpetiall meanes to procure God's bleſſing both upon King and people; as may be ſeen in the examples of the good
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119628:51"/> Kinges of Judah, when they brake downe the Images, put away the Sodomites and witches &amp;c out of their land (2 Cron. 30: 14. and 34: 33. and 33: 15.) and in Jehu the king of Iſrael, who is commended for pulling downe the temple of Baal, &amp;c. (2 King. 10: 26. 27. 28.) though he abode in the ſin of Jeroboam ſtill: and for his ſervice herein, and deſtroying the houſe of Ahab, he had the kingdome of Iſrael confirmed to his ſons to the fourth generation. We ſee then how much it concerneth princes, to looke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the people committed to their charge, and how they ſhould with Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon crave of the Almightie <note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 3: 9.</note> 
               <hi>a wiſe and underſtanding heart</hi> to diſcerne between good and evill, to uphold and maintaine them that doe well, but to drive from their courts, counſels, and countenance, all diſhoneſtie, and iniquity, all oppreſſion and evill doeing, that ſo their thrones may be eſtabliſhed with Juſtice. And <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> for our owne parts to whom this is ſpoken (that we may not goe away without ſome particuler application of this to our ſelves) let us conſider what great thinges <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the Lord hath done for our ſoules, in that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119628:52"/> he hath placed us in this Country, where though we live among a people of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeech, yet God hath bin pleaſed ſo to inclyne the hearts both of princes and people, that we live a peaceable life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and amongſt them: Let us not then receave ſuch great good from the hands of God, without rendering due thankes and praiſe to him for this good gift which he hath beſtowed upon us. Conſider what miſery and affliction our friends and brethren in our native country do ſuffer at preſent, while we enjoy felicity and quiet. Oh, that our ingratitude, and careleſſe walking, deprive us not of it! Secondly, let us know that we are bound <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to pray for the magiſtrates and people of the land, by whoſe good will (next under God) we enjoy this. Let therfore their trouble be our trouble, and let us pray to God for them as for our ſelves; let their deliverances be our deliverances, and let us give thankes to God for whatſoever good is beſtowed upon them knowing that <hi>in</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 29: 7. 3.</note> 
               <hi>their peace we have peace.</hi> And laſtly ſeing we enjoy here a peaceable and quiet life, let us walke in all godlines and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. Have we quietnes &amp; freedome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:119628:52"/> conſcience to meet togither to ſerve God without let? let us then take heed how we turne this grace of God into wantonneſſe, how we abuſe this peaceable life we have from them, by an unquiet life among our ſelves. Be therfore zealous of everie good worke, carefull of ſanctifying the Lords day, making his ſabbath a delight unto us, ſpending it altogither in the ſervice of God publikely and privately: and towards men let our converſation be in all tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſobriety and equity, not doeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to any, <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12: 17. 18.</note> recompencing no man evill for evill, but as much as in us is live peaceably with all men. Let our <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5: 16.</note> 
               <hi>light ſo shine before men that they may ſee our good works and glorifie our father which is in heaven.</hi> For the grace of God that <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2: 12. 12. 13. 14.</note> bringeth ſalvation, hath appeared to all men, teaching us that denying ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquitie, and purifie unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good workes.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:119628:53"/>
            <p>A word or two more and then I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Is it ſo that magiſtrates have ſuch a charge, and duty, layd upon them, as hath bin before intimated: it followeth then that they have power and authority given them of God for the diſcharge hereof, if the Lord give them grace and wiſdome to mynd, underſtand, &amp; practiſe what is their duty, in that way and after that manner, which he in his word hath required: and then it may ſerve to teach us to be obedient to them in the Lord; to honour and reverence them in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of their office, and to give God thankes for them when he doth put into their hearts, to further and promote peace, godlines, and honeſty, in their realmes. Rom. 13: 1. 2. 3. Tit. 3: 1. 1 Pet. 2: 13. 14. 15. And it may ſerve for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the man of ſin, who doth trample the dignity of Kinges under his feet, and doth yeild no ſubjection to them: but exalteth himſelf <note n="l" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2: 4.</note> 
               <hi>above all that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God.</hi> It alſo reproveth the error of thoſe falſe prophets who teach &amp; ſay that ſubjection came in with ſin, and Chriſt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> having taken away ſin he hath alſo taken away ſubjection; and they are called unto
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119628:53"/> liberty therfore muſt not be the ſervants of men &amp;c, concluding thence an exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the power of the civile magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. Wherein they doe abuſe the word <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſvv. </seg>
               </label> of God, in making no difference between that civile ſubjection, which is for the maintainance of the order and peace of States and Countries, and ſlaviſh ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection a puniſhment for ſin. For a Chriſtian doth not obey the magiſtrate for feare and through terrour (as doe the wicked who are ſtill in their ſins, for whoſe ſake <note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1: 9. 10.</note> both the law and civile magiſtracie is appointed as a curbe and bridle to reſtraine their wicked and rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous deſires, who els would readily breake foorth to commit rapine, murder, inceſt, and all manner of filthineſſe without ſhame and remorſe even openly and with high hand againſt God) but for conſcience ſake towards God, who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded <hi>every</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13: 1</note> 
               <hi>ſoul to be ſubject to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God, and the powers that be are ordayned of God.</hi> As for our redemption by Chriſt, it is true, we are redeemed by him from the ſervice of ſin, and ſet free to ſerve him in <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1: 74. 75.</note> righteouſnes and holynes all the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119628:54"/> dayes of our life. And therfore we hold that ſo long as the magiſtrate doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that which is agreable to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and true holynes ſo long we are bound to obey actively; and this commandement is not grievous unto us, becaus it is that which God commandeth: but when he commandeth otherwiſe, then we may &amp; muſt anſwere, as the Apoſtles did in the like caſe, <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 4: 19.</note> 
               <hi>it is better to obey God than man;</hi> in ſuch caſes we are bound patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any puniſhment or perſecution at their handes, willingly ſubmitting our ſelves unto death it ſelf, rather than to diſpleaſe our heavenlie father. And ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as we thus behave our ſelves we ſhall neither bring our ſelves in bondage to ſin (for to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a man yeildeth himſelf ſervant to obey, his ſervant he is whom he obeyeth) or incurre the puniſhment of ſin. But they whoſoever they be that under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and the cloake of Chriſtian liberty and religion, doe teach any doctrine that leadeth to rebellion againſt anie miniſter of God in the lawfull diſcharge of his duty; they are ſo farre from ſtanding faſt in the <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5: 1.</note> libertie wherewith Chriſt hath made them free; that they intangle
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119628:54"/> themſelves againe with the yoake of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: and while they <note n="r" place="margin">2 <hi>Pot.</hi> 2: 19.</note> promiſe men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption: for of whomſoever a man is overcome of the ſame is he brought in bondage. And whiles they break the <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5: 19.</note> leaſt of the words of Chriſt, and teach men ſo; it is to be feared that they are the leaſt in the Kingdome of heaven. And it is a thing taught us by that great Doctor of the Church, and therfore muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved and obeyed as truth viz that we in giving unto Caeſar no more than what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to him, can not rob God of any thing of his: for theſe two muſt ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 22: 21.</note> 
               <hi>Give unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and unto God, the thinges that are Gods.</hi> What God hath joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither let no man put a ſunder. But <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> they will Object yet further, that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are in the kingdome of heaven here in this life, and therfore to be in obedience to none but to Chriſt their King? which is not farre diſcrepant from that which ſome have affirmed of late, that becaus Chriſt's kingdome is not from hence or of this world, and that to Chriſtians there is but one God: therfore no ſubjection or
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119628:55"/> ſuperioritie to be given to the prince in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes (i. e as themſelves have interpreted the dutyes required in the firſt table of the lawe) Wherein they erre greatly, (not knowing the ſcripture, nor the order wherein God hath ſet man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind here on earth both for the upholding of his Spirituall and civile eſtate, neither underſtanding well what they ſpeake or whereof they affirme) in that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave not that there are two kinds of goverment in this world, a thing ſo plaine as nothing is plainer. The one Spirituall, of Chriſt in his Church; in which reſpect all are to be in a like ſubjection unto Chriſt, both prince and people, noble men and them of lowe degree; and to be governed by ſuch officers and lawes, as the Lord Jeſus hath for that end inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and in this eſtate the prince and people are brethren, and of like liberty &amp; authoritie; neither maie they be maſters of one an others faith, <hi>but fellow helpers of each others joy.</hi> The other is civile or worldly in the common wealth; which governement is alſo of God, and ought to be adminiſtered according to his lawe, being the perfect rule of righteouſnes,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119628:55"/> according to which all humane lawes ought to be made, or els Judgment and juſtice can not be rightly executed. In which eſtate we are to be conſidered in ſeverall degrees and conditions, as namely, one is a prince or King, the reſt are the ſubjects and people; ſome are magiſtrates, others are thoſe under their gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; one is a father, an other a child; one a maſter, an other a ſervant; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe relations, the inferiour is to be in ſubjection to the Superiour in the Lord. To denie the power of the magiſtrate in the common wealth, were to inforce a denyall of the power of maſters and fathers in their familyes, ſeing one and<note place="margin">5 <hi>Com.</hi>
               </note> the ſame commandement of the lawe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth ſubjection to the one as well as the other; and ſo to bring the fabrick of natures-order, which God hath ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully made, and ſo wiſely and orderly diſpoſed, to a confuſed chaos. So that Chriſtians to avoyd this abſurdity, muſt neceſſarily mynd themſelves every one while he liveth in the world in any gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned city, Countrie, province, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, to beare or repreſent a double perſon or eſtate. 1. A member of the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119628:56"/> church, wherein his dignity and honour ſpiritually in the ſight of God is as great as any other member or officer in the ſame body, and greater than any King or prince of the world that is not a member of the Church of Chriſt. 2. A member of the common wealth, a citizen of the city, an Inhabitant of the towne, or a member of the familie; wherein he is either ſuperiour or inferiour. If fuperior; to rule and governe thoſe committed to his charge, according to the will of God, <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 4: 1.</note> 
               <hi>doeing to every one that which is juſt and equall; knowing that he hath alſo a maſter in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> If inferior, he is to be ſubject and obedient to all thinges that are agreable to the word of God, whither they be things Spirituall or temporall; and that not for feare but for conſcience ſake, <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 6: 6. 7. 8.</note> 
               <hi>not as men pleaſers, but in ſinglenes of heart as unto Chriſt, knowing that of the Lord they shall receave their reward whither they be bond or free; for in ſo doeing they ſerve</hi> (not men properly but) <hi>the Lord Chriſt.</hi> Thus we may ſee how the eſtate of a Chriſtian doth not overthrow but rather eſtabliſh the order of nature, and the civile govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this life. But indeed thus much
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119628:56"/> maie be intimated, by waie of concluſion; that if it could ſo come to paſſe (which we have no ground to expect) that a whole land or citie were (both magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and people, high and low) all faithfull and ſincere Chriſtians, diligently obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the rules of Chriſt for the redreſſe of things amiſſe at anie time, there would be ſo little uſe of civile power, as if it were a needleſſe adminiſtration. But ſeing God hath in his divine wiſdome fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, that after the fall and tranſgreſſion of Adam, there would be alwayes a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of beleevers and Infidels in the world; and that the wicked ſhould be as pricks and thornes in the eyes and ſides of his Saints to try their faith and patience; and hath to the end that the wickednes of men (who are ready by nature to break forth into blood oppreſſion, and open violence to the deſtruction of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which God hath made, and which it ſtandeth him in hand to preſerve, that ſo his mercy may be ſeen both to juſt and unjuſt) may be reſtrayned and kept in ſome order, appointed Kinges princes and eſtates, with the good will and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the people, to rule and governe,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119628:57"/> that the wronged may have right, and the oppreſſed may be delivered, and violent wrong-doers may be terrified by the ſword of Juſtice; and it hath bin, is, and ſhalbe allwayes the portion of the little flock of Chriſt to have their reſidence or ſojourning in ſome Common wealth or other: let us therfore admire the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wiſdome of God in thus reſtayning the rage of man; and let us be ſo farre from <note n="y" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2: 10.</note> deſpiſeing governements or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, as that <hi>for conſcience towards God wee doe ſubmit our ſelves unto all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ordinances of men for the Lord's ſake,</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet. 2: 13. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>whither it be to the King, as unto the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Preame, or unto governors, as unto them that are ſent of him, for the punishment of evill doers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well. For ſo is the will of God, that by w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll-doeing we may put to ſilence the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of foolish men, as free, and not having the libertie for a cloake of malitiouſnes, but as the ſervants of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119628:57"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 Pet. 2: 7.</bibl>
                  <p>Feare God, honour the King.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Prov. 24: 21.</bibl>
                  <p>My ſon feare thou the Lord and the King: and meddle not with them that are given to change.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:119628:58"/>
            <head>A poſtſcript wherein ſome thing is ſpoken not altogither unworthy of conſideration in theſe times.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving taken in hand thus farre to ſpeak unto thee (loving reader) have pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience till I have uttered a few words more, and then judge as the Lord ſhall give thee diſcerning. I have heard and read manie grievous complaints ſince the ſitting of this preſent Parliament againſt Browniſts and Browniſtically af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, as the great enemies at this day in common accompt, againſt whom almoſt all mens mouthes are open both to King and Parliament, as if they were the only cockle, darnell, &amp; evill weeds, the unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable branches, which hinder the growth of the good corne, and ſpoile the vine of of the common wealth; and as yet I have not ſeen or heard anie information or diſcription, what they be for men and women that may rightly and truly be ſo named; for countenanceing and favouring of whom the Parliament hath bin much
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119628:58"/> complayned of; and yet for ought I know they are at a great ſtand about the true knowledge of that ſect, ſeing by their owne confeſſion, all <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſvv. to K declar. of vict. Octo.</hi> 3. 1642.</note> well affected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are called by that name. Foraſmuch therfore as they have bin only hitherto named, but their nature not defyned, yea that hath bin a nick-name caſt upon thoſe to whom it doth not of right belong; I ſhall with as much brevity as I can (mynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unworthines of the ſubject) ſet the ſaddle upon the right horſe, and that not as an <note n="*" place="margin">Ad conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ne acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeris ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam voceris.</note> advertiſer to the King or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (for <hi>who am I that I should ſpeake unto Pharaoh?</hi> Exod. 3: 11.) but as a well willer to the common people, and one that deſireth to doe my countrie good (or at leaſt to labour the diſcharge of myne owne conſcience) and therein I hope I ſhall approve my ſelfe loyall and faithfull both to the one and the other. It is (we know) a receaved cuſtome in the world, to call the men of one ſect, religion, or faction, after the name of thoſe that have bin chief broachers, maintayners, or faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt witneſſes thereof (and not of ſuch as returne againe from their receaved practiſe to their former courſe) as the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119628:59"/> Nicholaitanes are called of Nicholas, who was their falſe Apoſtle; Lutheranes are ſo called of Luther, who was a faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the light which was revealed to him; Calviniſts of Calvin, who was an able and worthy inſtrument of ſpreading the light which he ſaw; and ſo Arminians of Arminius, which was a cunning de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaver, &amp; ſtood ſtoutly to profeſſe, teach, and publiſh the falſe doctrines unto which he fell away; &amp;c: or els they are called after the falſe doctrines which they teach as Anabaptiſts becaus they deny bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of infants, and men of age though they have once receaved true outward baptiſme yet coming to them muſt be againe baptiſed; papiſts becauſe they hold the doctrine of the pope and church of Rome, and honour the pope as head of the Church &amp;c. So I alſo take that generally the common people in England and elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, doe underſtand by Browniſts or Browniſtically affected (ſeing the name can not agree to anie point of doctrine) ſuch as doe follow that doctrine and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which one Browne was a prime author witnes and conſtant maintayner of by word and writing: which to prove
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119628:59"/> concerning the doctrine and diſcipline profeſſed by thoſe who ſeperate from the church of England as a falſe Church, not daring to have any communion with her. for feare of defyling their garments) and hold the diſcipline of every true church to be independant, would be hard for any of thoſe that ſo call them, be they never ſo learned hiſtory-graphers to doe.</p>
            <p>But indeed thus much I confeſſe, that I have both heard and read of one Browne who lived about the latter end of Q: Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, or beginning of K. James his raigne, and had receaved once ſome taſt of the good word of God, and made ſome profeſſion of the truth; but afterwards revolted from the countenanceing of the way of God (it ſeemeth for the <note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4: 10.</note> 
               <hi>love of the world</hi>) and turned like the dog to his old vomit; for he tooke againe upon him his Antichriſtian miniſtery, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced the Church of England to his death, though I have alſo heard, that when he hath bin put upon it in diſcourſe to ſhew reaſons againſt the way which he did ſo diſcountenance, he could ſay little or nothing: yet becaus of the fleſh pots of Egypt, the garlick and the onyons
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119628:60"/> wherewith his belly was filled (and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (it may be) taſted or ſeene the poverty of the Saints, and hatred of men againſt them which is one of their <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16: 33.</note> badges here in this world) he was loth to leave it by perſonall ſeperation. Wherfore I ſee little ground why the profeſſors of ſeper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation ſhould be called after his name as if they were his diſciples. But rather I conceave, &amp; I have the witnes not of man but of God in my behalf, that he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againe to the ſtate of the Church of England, and dyeing in the teſtimony thereof, countenanceing it by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and ſociety therein, and being a preacher thereof; hath thereby manifeſted to the world and to men, <hi>that</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2: 19.</note> 
               <hi>he was not of us: for if he had bin of us he would no doubt have continued with us: but he went out from us that he might be made manifeſt that he was not of us.</hi> Whence I conclude that they may according to the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word (more properly than any) be called Browniſts, who for the love of their earthly benefits, and to avoyd the hatred of men, doe continue ſtill in, or returne againe unto the countenanceing of the Antichriſtian eſtate wherein the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119628:60"/> Church of England was at that time; and thoſe indeed are they that are Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtically affected i. e. affected as Browne was. Wherfore my hope is that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the high court of Parliament ſhall proceed to their well ſetled reformation (though I expect not that by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of men the truth of God ſhalbe ever eſtabliſhed in the ſincere profeſſion thereof, and that becaus the Lord himſelf ſaith <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 110: 2.</note> 
               <hi>that his people shalbe voluntaries in the day of his power;</hi> and our Saviour plainly declareth that <hi>no man</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6: 44.</note> 
               <hi>can come to him but whom the father draweth,</hi> for it is <hi>not</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 4: 6.</note> 
               <hi>by might</hi> (or armies) <hi>nor by power, but by my Spirit,</hi> ſaith the Lord of hoſts) they will manifeſt to the world their utter diſlike of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>P. Anſvv. to the K. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar. of his vict. Oct. 3. 1642. pag.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Browniſme according to the reall and proper ſignification of the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> that is thoſe that follow Browne in the countenanceing and approving of the man of ſin &amp; his Antichriſtian Hierarchie. And to this underſtanding of this nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name they are neceſſarily bound by the rule of charity upon their owne grounds: for if they hold ſeperation from the Church of England to be an error, and that Browne was once in that way; then
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119628:61"/> when afterward he returned from that, and gave them ſuch ſatiſfaction as that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved again his miniſterie, he repented of his former error. Now for to make him a patrone or father of that whereof he repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and which he caſt off, is a great breach of charity, not beſeeming ſuch as accompt themſelves miniſters of Chriſt to put upon their follow-labourers. I have ſpoken thus much upon this ſlight occaſion only for this end that the profeſſors of the truth &amp; all that are well mynded may take notice, that there is at this day no religion, hereſy, ſect, or faction, that doth ſo unjuſtly and improperly beare the name wherewith they are uſually named by their oppoſites, as doth this poore deſpiſed people. But let them be comforted that it is for Chriſt's ſake, &amp; their ſeperation from the unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full works of darkneſſe that they are ſo named, and happie are they therein, for great ſhalbe their reward in heaven.</p>
            <p>I have perceived alſo now in theſe dayes of <hi>England's</hi> trouble, the preſſes to be imployed more freely than they have bin in times paſt; and many are bold to publiſh their conceits, and opinions in matter of <hi>Religion,</hi> and to be counſillors
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:119628:61"/> &amp; admonitors to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that high &amp; honourable court, which is the great Counſill of the Kingdom, how they ſhould behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and what they ſhould inclyne to, in their reformation of <hi>Church-goverment.</hi> Which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe ſeem to me, to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d labour, and trouble that Court, in vain; for if they did rightly conſider the nature of Chriſt's kingdome, they need not ſeeke unto men, but (if they be ſervants of God, they need only to ſeeke) unto him who is <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nom.</hi> 27: 16.</note> 
               <hi>God of the ſpirits of all flesb,</hi> to ſend forth his word, with the power and demonſtration of his good Spirit, which would be (as indeed it is) the onlie and ſuffitient way and meanes for planting and eſtabliſhing of his true Church; and only adviſe the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to approve themſelves the miniſters of God in ſuffering his truth to flouriſh, and cheriſhing the profeſſors of the ſame; and to reſtrain (by their power) the malice of wicked perſecutors, (as did that noble King <hi>Darius</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who commanded the enemyes beyond the river <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 6: 6. 7. 11. 12.</note> to be farr from hindering the Jewes from building the houſe of God, yea whoſoever (ſaith he) ſhall alter this word, let timber be pulled downe from
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119628:62"/> his houſe, and being ſet up, let him be hanged thereon, and his houſe be made a dunghill for this. And the God that hath cauſed his name to dwell there, deſtroy all Kings and people, that ſhall put to their hand to alter and to deſtroy this houſe of God which is at Jeruſalem) and to make ſuch wholſome and good lawes, as might inable and authoriſe the civill magiſtrates, and Courts of juſtice <note n="*" place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Nevv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comen in his ſerm: before the Parl: 5 November 1642. pag. 44. Next to this as a ſecond means for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing of popery, I vvould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn the caſting out from among us all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, every thing that looks like Rome, every thing of vvhich the papiſts may ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This you borrovved from us, &amp;c. I condemne not every thing receaved from Rome as ſimply evill, but certainly as long as the papists ſee any ſuch things among us in our publike vvorsbip, they vvill but ſcorn us, and our religion as imperfect, and unable to furnish us in the ſervice of our God vvithout being beholding to them. If ye knovv theſe things happy are ye if ye doe them. Iohn. 13: 17.</note> in all parts of the kingdome to demoliſh all Idolatrous reliques, and ſuperſtitious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, (as they have already moſt worthily begun with that great Image of many faces in Cheapſide) to puniſh open Idolatrie, blaſphemie, ſwearing, curſing, Sabbath-breaking, and all ſuch as are <hi>lawleſſe, diſobedient, traytors, ungodly, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners unholy, prophane, murderers of fathers, murderers of mothers, manſlayers, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, defylers of themſelves with mankind, men ſtealers, lyers, periured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 1: 9. 10. but to uphold
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119628:62"/> and maintaine thoſe that walke godly, righteouſly, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2: 12.</note> ſoberlie among them, though it ſhould not be juſt in that way and manner of publike worſhip, which the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall ſet up. For I can not but hold well of that which that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and able miniſter of the goſpel <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Henry Aynſworth</hi> hath long ſince writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (Counterpoy: Pag. 232.) concerning the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> ſaying, How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever all ſubjects are, and ought, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the good civill lawes there inacted, and obedience may be inforced by the ſword (Rom. 13.) if any reſiſt: yet in caſes of conſcience every man muſt live by his owne faith, Hab. 2: 4. Nen muſt gladly receave the word (Act. 2: 41.) out of which all religion muſt be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all Kings and Kingdomes ſubmitting unto the lawes and ordinances in Chriſts teſtament, (Pſal. 2: 10. 11. 12.) if they would have bleſſing and ſalvation by him. With which agreeth well that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent note of an antient writer (and there are many that reverence antiquity in matter of religion, and indeed it is the old way, in walking wherein we find reſt) who teacheth us that <note n="m" place="margin">Bern: in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>fides ſuadenda
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119628:63"/> eſt, non imperanda.</hi> For the Apoſtle plainly declareth that none can <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10: 14. 15. 17.</note> 
               <hi>call upon him in whom they have not beleeved, neither can they believe in him of whom they have not heard, and heare they can not without a preacher, and none can preach except he be ſent of God,</hi> and furniſhed for that ſervice; So that <hi>faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God,</hi> not by the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements or traditions of men, which are of no ſuch power to perſwade the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as the word of God is. And if the heart &amp; conſcience be not perſwaded in feare of God to yeild obedience, what will come of it, but an inforced hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, a drawing neare to God with the lip, when the heart is farre from him? which is a ſervice abominable in his ſight, and wherein there can be no true inward comfort and aſſurance, which is the life and marrow of religion, and that which begetteth true loyaltie to the higher powers. For ſurely it is a true ſaying that was once ſpoken unto this preſent Parliament in a publike ſermon by one of their owne miniſters Junij 20. 1641. viz That <hi>there are a great many miniſters that are not reſolved what to doe &amp;c., they
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119628:63"/> will wait for what the Parliament will doe, you may ſet up what religion you pleaſe they will be of your religion ſtill.</hi> So alſo may be ſaid of others, they wilbe of what religion the king is of, ſo long as he hath any power to ſupport them and any boones or offices to give them. Yea ſome think it high preſumption to be of any other mynd that way, than the king or Parliament is of. If this be not a ſerving God after the will of man, I know not what is. Let us not therefore <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14: 13.</note> 
               <hi>judge one an other any more: but judge this rather that no man put a ſtumbling block, or an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to fall in his brothers way;</hi> but <hi>let every man be fully perſwaded in his mynd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vers</hi> 5: 23.</note> and doe no thing without faith in this kind, for <hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſin,</hi> and <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11: 6.</note> 
               <hi>without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> Now <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2: 8.</note> 
               <hi>faith is the gift of God,</hi> wrought in the heart by his holy Spirit, uſeing thereto (as the outward meanes thereof) the miniſtery of the word of reconciliation; and be ſure of this, that ſo ſoone as the heart is truly moved by the work of the Spirit, there cannot but be a moſt free and readie joyning to the Lord in faithfull ſubmiſſion to his will,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119628:64"/> for ſaith the Spouſe, <hi>Draw me</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 1: 4.</note> 
               <hi>and we will run after thee,</hi> and the prophet David, <hi>I will run the way</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119: 32.</note> 
               <hi>of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements when thou shalt inlarge myne heart.</hi> And untill the heart of the people be moved all that the kings and parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the earth can doe by their outward force and power, ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile to eſtabliſh the ſervice of God in its due and right order; yea though they ſhould be as godly and zealous as <hi>Iehosha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> the King of Judah, of whom the ſcripture noteth that he walked in the way of Aſa his father, and departed not from it, doeing that which was right in the ſight of the Lord: <note n="t" place="margin">2 <hi>Cron,</hi> 20: 32. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Howbeit the high places were not taken away: for as yet the people had not prepared their hearts unto the God of their fathers.</hi> And if ſuch a zealous and powerfull prince as K. Jehoſhaphat could not prevaile in the reformation of externall and viſible abuſes in religious worſhip, and that becaus the peoples hearts were not prepared &amp;c: Much leſſe ſhall anie earthly prince or potentate be able by his worldly power to make this people to <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4: 23.</note> 
               <hi>worship the father in Spirit and truth, and ſuch he ſeeketh to worship
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119628:64"/> him.</hi> The reaſon is becaus the kingdom of Chriſt is not of this world, neither can be planted or eſtabliſhed by worldly power, for <hi>ſo long as the vaile</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3: 13.</note> 
               <hi>is over mens hearts, they can not looke to the end of that which is abolished,</hi> but when the Lord ſhall mollifie their hard and ſtony hearts, and give unto them hearts of fleſh, when he ſhall enlighten their myndes and open their underſtandings, and ſo turne them <hi>from Idols to ſerve the living and true God</hi> then the vaile ſhall be taken away. Now the Lord is <note n="y" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3: 16. 17.</note> that ſpirit, and where the Spirit of the Lord is there is liberty, to wit, from the bondage of ſin to ſerve God in righteouſnes and holynes all the days of their life. Gal. 5: 1. Rom. 6: 22. &amp; 7. 6. Luc. 1: 74. 75. Wherefore that was a good decree of King Cyrus who being appointed to build the Lord an houſe in Jeruſalem, did not force or compell all his people to ſet on that work, but gave out proclamation ſaying <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 1: 3.</note> 
               <hi>who is there among you of all his people? his God be with him and let him goe up to Ieruſalem which is in Iudah, and build the houſe of the Lord God of Iſrael &amp;c.</hi> and the text ſaith afterwards <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vers</hi> 5.</note> Then roſe up the chief of the fathers &amp;c,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119628:65"/> with all them whoſe ſpirit God had raiſed to goe up to build the houſe of the Lord which is in Jeruſalem. With which agreeth the decree of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> after that, which he ſent unto Ezra the Scribe ſaying <hi>I</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eza.</hi> 7: 13.</note> 
               <hi>make a decree that all they of the people of Iſraell and of his prieſts, and levites in my realme which are mynded of their owne free will to goe up to Ieruſalem goe with thee.</hi> For indeed this is a thing that muſt needs be done, before the ſervice of the houſe of God can be ſet in order, to wit, that there ſhould be a people fitted and prepared by the Lord for the making of his temple, &amp; theſe ſtones muſt be hewea in the mountayne, they muſt be fitted and prepared before they can be joyned into the holy covenant. Of this fitting &amp; preparing neither the K nor parliament can be competent Judges, but they muſt be thoſe workmen, that have ſquared them for the building which muſt judge of their fitneſſe, they muſt be men learned and expert in the ſcripture (which is the golden rod, or rule, the line, and plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, where by the matter of this ſpirituall houſe is tryed) that muſt be the maſons and workmen, that muſt be the overſeers
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119628:65"/> and chief rulers in this worke. And when they are fitted, ther muſt be a willing gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves to the Lord, and adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one to another, to ſerve God with one conſent; they muſt not be drawen by force, it muſt be the love of God that muſt conſtrayne them, or all will be loſt labour. Wherfore the Jews when their adverſaries would by fraud &amp; deceit have thruſt themſelves into the worke of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they would not permit it, but ſaid <hi>You</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4: 3.</note> 
               <hi>have nothing to doe with us, to build an houſe unto our God; but we our ſelves togither will build unto the Lord God of Iſrael, as King Cyrus the king of Perſia hath commanded us.</hi> And be ſure God will not neglect his owne worke, but in his good time will inlighten the myndes of his elect, and call them to the knowledge of his truth. And for them that are not of that nomber, what have they to doe ſaith God, <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> 
               <hi>to take my covenant in their lips ſeing they hate to be reformed?</hi> Thus for the Parliament to behave themſelves in point of religion, I doubt not but would be an eſpetiall meanes to bring peace to their Kingdome, free them from that ſin where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the man of ſin is declared guilty, who
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119628:66"/> ſitteth as God in the temple of God, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and compelling the conſciences of men by his laws and canons, when the canon of the Scripture is neglected or receaved but in the ſecond place; and to make this the moſt renowned parliament that ever was aſſembled in that land. It would eaſe them and the whole land of great trouble and expence, if they would only looke to the Civile governement of the land according to the law of God, and the juſt lawes of the Kingdome; and take off that yoke of oppreſſion which hath bin by former parliaments layd upon the conſciences of the free-borne ſubjects of that Kingdome, who have by the law of the land (or by the miſunderſtanding of the Judges of the law) bin excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, fyned, impriſoned, baniſhed, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally puniſhed, yea and ſome put to death, for diſſenting and ſeperating from their Idolatrous and Antichriſtian aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. Then ſhould their faſting be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted before the Lord, and their prayers be heard on high (or at leaſt the prayers of God's people for them) and I can not be otherwiſe perſwaded, but that then the Lord would ſoone be moved to turne
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119628:66"/> away his wrath, which now is burning againſt that nation: for <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58: 6. 7. 8. 9. 12.</note> 
               <hi>is not this thefaſt</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>that I have choſen? to looſe the bands of wickednes, to undoe the heavie burdens, and to let the oppreſſed goe free, and that ye breake every yoke? Is it not to deale thy bread to the hungrie, and that thou bring the poore that are caſt out to thyne houſe? when thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou cover him, and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thine owne flesh? Then shall thy light breake forth as the morning, and thine health shall ſpring forth ſpeedily: and thy righteouſnes shall goe before thee, and the glory of the Lord shalbe thy rereward. Then shalt thou call, and the Lord shall anſwere: thou shalt cry, and he shall ſay, Here am I. if thou take from the midst of thee the yoke, the putting forth of the finger, and ſpeaking vanity &amp;c. And they shalbe of thee that shall build the old waſt places: thou shalt raiſe up the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of many generations, and thou shalt be called the repairer of the breach, the reſtorer of pathes to dwell in.</hi> By this meanes alſo they ſhould ſoone finde out who are the <hi>Achans</hi> that bring trouble upon the Kingdome, and the lawes and Courts of juſtice might ſeize upon, and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119628:67"/> puniſh them. For liberty being thus given unto men (or more properly, men being left to the work of God's word and Spirit, in matter (or rather manner) of religion, and nothing impoſed upon them by the State, but only injunctions to walke orderly and juſtly) it would ſoone appeare who are the faithfull ſubjects, who are they that are obedient to Kinges and thoſe in authority, who are they that wiſh moſt the good of the land; and on the contrary, who are they that deſerve to be puniſhed, impriſoned, and (if their fault ſo require) baniſhed, namely, <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 101: 8.</note> 
               <hi>the wicked if the land;</hi> thoſe that live in ryot and drunckeneſſe, in chambering &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, in ſwearing, curſing, Idolatry, Sabbath-breaking, oppreſſion and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie; for they are thoſe who (being left unpuniſhed or countenanced by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) bring downe God's judgments upon a nation; and not thoſe that <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12: 13.</note> feare God, labour to keepe his commandements, and ſeeke to ſave their ſoules, by <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nom.</hi> 16: 26.</note> ſeperating from the Communion and ſociety of ſuch wicked perſons, as are before named. For theſe are the righteous, who by their prayers, and teares, upon all occaſions, doe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119628:67"/> turne away the wrath of God, and ſave the City or Country wherein they dwell. Job 22: 30. Eccleſ. 9: 15. Gen. 18: 25. &amp;c. Geneſ. 30: 27. Acts. 27: 24. Theſe few words have I uttered further, out of zeal to God, love to my native Country, honour to my prince, and that honourable Court of Parliament, and for the diſcharge of myne owne conſcience, that it may not be at that day layd to my charge that I had once a time to ſpeak, and held my peace. And I beſeech Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to turn away his fierce wrath from our land, to give his goſpell a free paſſage, that the kingdome of his ſon may be increaſed, and the kingdome of Satan, and Antichriſt be more and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by the ſword of his mouth, and at<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> length wholie deſtroyed by the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his coming; that we may with the Apoſtle John heare that great voice of much people in heaven, ſaying <hi>Alleluja,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19: 1. 2. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſalvation, and glory, and honour and power unto the Lord our God: For true and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous are his judgments, for he hath judged the great whore which did corrupt the earth with her fornication, and hath avenged the bloud of his ſervants at her hand. And
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119628:68"/> again they ſaid, Alleluja: and her ſmoke roſe up for ever. And the four and twenty elders and the four beasts fell downe, and worshiped God, that ſate on the throne, ſaying, Amen, Alleluja.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:119628:68"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 1. l. 12. r In vindication. pag. 18. l. 23. r ſtop. pag. 33. l. 13. r warfare. pag. 40. l. 14. r vers 5. &amp;c. pag. 53. l. 19. r <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> pag. 54. l. 17. r nor pag. 61. l. 10. r</hi> watch <hi>pag. 64. margent r</hi> miſericordia. <hi>pag. 97. 8. is</hi> a myſterie. <hi>pag. 117. l. 4. put out. pag. 120. l. 2. r ſatiſfaction pag. 121. l. 1. put out. pag. 123. l. 16. r. men pag. 126. l. 26. r make his.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
